<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="no"?>
<?rfc private="DRAFT"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc
        SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<rfc>
    <front>
        <title>SCIM PROTOCOL</title>

        <author initials="T.D." surname="Drake" fullname="Trey Drake" role="editor">
            <organization abbrev="UnboundID">UnboundID</organization>
            <address>
                <email>trey.drake@unboundid.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="C.M." surname="Mortimore" fullname="Chuck Mortimore">
            <organization abbrev="SalesForce">SalesForce</organization>
            <address>
                <email>cmortimore@salesforce.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <date month="May" year="2011"/>
        <keyword>SCIM</keyword>
        <abstract>
            <t>
                The Simple Cloud Identity Management (SCIM) specification is designed to make managing user identity in
                cloud based applications and services easier. The specification suite seeks to build upon experience
                with existing schemas and deployments, placing specific emphasis on simplicity of development and
                integration, while applying existing authentication, authorization, and privacy models. It's intent is
                to reduce the cost and complexity of user management operations by providing a common user schema and
                extension model, as well as binding documents to provide patterns for exchanging this schema using
                standard protocols. In essence, make it fast, cheap, and easy to move users in to, out of, and around
                the cloud.

                This document provides a REST API for exchanging user identity via JSON and/or XML
            </t>
        </abstract>
    </front>


    <middle>
        <section title="Introduction and Overview" anchor="intro" toc="default">
            <t>The SCIM Protocol is an application-level, REST protocol for provisioning and managing user identity on the web. The protocol supports
                creating, editing, deleting, querying and retrieving User resources.
            </t>

            <section title="Intended Audience" toc="default">
                <t>
                    This document is intended as a guide to SCIM API usage for both user identity providers and
                    consumers.
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="Notational Conventions" anchor="notat" toc="default">
                <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT",
                    "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
                    [RFC2119].
                </t>

            </section>
            <section title="Definitions" anchor="defs" toc="default">
                <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="Service Provider:">A web application that provides User information via the SCIM
                        protocol.
                    </t>
                    <t hangText="Consumer:">A website or application that uses the SCIM protocol to manage Users managed
                        by the Service Provider.
                    </t>
                    <t hangText="Base URL:">The SCIM REST API is always relative to a Base URL for the API. The Base URL
                        MUST NOT contain any query string, as additional path information and query string variables MAY
                        be appended by Consumers as part of forming the request. Example: https://example.com/scim
                    </t>
                    <t hangText="Singular Field:">A User field that can appear at most once per User, e.g.displayName.
                    </t>
                    <t hangText="Plural Field:">A User field that can appear multiple times per User, e.g. emails</t>
                    <t hangText="Simple Field:">A Singular Field or Plural Field whose value is a single string
                        attribute.
                    </t>
                    <t hangText="Complex Field:">A Singular Field or Plural Field whose value is an object containing
                        multiple sub-field attributes.
                    </t>
                    <t hangText="Primary Sub-Value:">The sub-field in a Complex Field that should be used when sorting
                        or filtering by that field. Unless otherwise specified, the value sub-field is always the
                        Primary Sub-Field.
                    </t>
                </list>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Authentication and Authorization" anchor="aa" toc="default">
            <t>
                Authentication to the SCIM REST API is performed using OAuth2:
                http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-oauth-v2-15
            </t>
            <t>
                For example:
            </t>
            <figure height="" suppress-title="false" width="" alt="" title="" align="left">
                <artwork height="" name="" width="" type="" alt="" align="left" xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[
            GET /resource/1 HTTP/1.1
            Host: example.com
            Authorization: Bearer h480djs93hd8
                                   ]]></artwork>
            </figure>
            <t>
                The context of the request (i.e. the user for whom data is being requested) MUST be inferred by Service
                Providers from the Base URL and the authorization credentials provided. The same Base URL MAY return
                information for different users depending on the authorization credentials provided.
            </t>


        </section>

        <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="Security" toc="default">
            <t>Securing the protocol:TBD</t>
        </section>


        <section title="API" anchor="api">
            <t>
                The SCIM protocol specifies well known endpoints and operations for managing User and User discovery
                resources via standard HTTP methods:
            </t>
            <list style="hanging">
                <t hangText="GET">Retrieves a complete or partial User/Schema
                </t>
                <t hangText="POST">Creates a new User
                </t>
                <t hangText="PUT">Modifies a User with a complete, consumer specified User (replace)
                </t>
                <t hangText="PATCH">Modifies a User with a set of consumer specified changes (partial update)
                </t>
                <t hangText="DELETE">Deletes a User.
                </t>
            </list>

            <texttable anchor='endpoint-summary' title="Defined endpoints">
                <preamble></preamble>
                <ttcol align='left'>Resource</ttcol>
                <ttcol align='left'>Endpoint</ttcol>
                <ttcol align='left'>Operations</ttcol>
                <ttcol align='left'>Description</ttcol>
                <c>User</c>
                <c>/User</c>
                <c><xref target="get-user" format="default">GET</xref>,
                    <xref target="create-user" format="default">POST</xref>,
                    <xref target="edit-user-with-put" format="default">PUT</xref>,
                    <xref target="edit-user-with-patch" format="default">PATCH</xref>,
                    <xref target="delete-user" format="default">DELETE</xref>
                </c>
                <c>Read/Modify Users</c>

                <c>
                    User Query/Listing
                </c>
                <c>/Users</c>
                <c>
                    <xref target="query-users" format="default">GET</xref>
                </c>
                <c>Retrieve User via ad hoc queries</c>


                <c>User Schema</c>
                <c>
                    /Schema
                </c>
                <c>
                    <xref target="get-schema" format="default">GET</xref>
                </c>
                <c>Retrieve a specified User schema</c>

                <c>User Schemas</c>
                <c>
                    /Schemas
                </c>
                <c>
                    <xref target="get-schemas" format="default">GET</xref>
                </c>
                <c>Retrieve all Service Provider supported schemas</c>
            </texttable>

            <t>
                All requests to the Service Provider are made via
                <eref target="http://www.w3.org/Protocols/rfc2616/rfc2616-sec9.html#sec9">HTTP operations</eref>
                on a URL derived from the Base URL. Responses are returned in the body of the HTTP response, formatted
                as JSON or XML, depending on what is requested. Response and error codes SHOULD be transmitted via the
                HTTP status code of the response (if possible), and SHOULD also be specified in the body of the
                response.
            </t>

            <section title="Creating Users" anchor="create-user" toc="default">
                <t>To create new Users, clients send POST requests to the User endpoint /User.</t>

                <t>Successful User creation is indicated with a 201 ("Created") response code. Upon successful creation,
                    the response body MUST contain the newly created Resource. Since the server is free to alter and/or
                    ignore POSTed content, returning the User can be useful to the client, enabling it to correlate the
                    client and server views of the new User.

                    When a User is created, its User URI must be returned in the response Location header.
                </t>

                <t>Below, the client sends a POST request containing a User</t>
                <figure height="" suppress-title="false" width="" alt="" title="" align="left">
                    <artwork height="" name="" width="" type="" alt="" align="left" xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[
POST /User  HTTP/1.1
Host: example.com
Content-Type:  application/json
Authorization: Bearer h480djs93hd8
Content-Length: ...

{
  "schemas": ["urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0"],
  "userName": "bjensen@example.com",
  "name": {
    "familyName": "Jensen",
    "givenName": "Barbara"
  },
  "displayName": "Babs Jensen", "emails": [
    {
      "value": "bjensen@example.com",
      "type": "work",
      "primary": true
    }
  ]
}
                        ]]></artwork>
                </figure>

                <t>The server signals a successful creation with a status code of 201. The response includes a Location
                    header indicating the User URI, and a representation of that User in the body of the response.
                </t>

                <figure height="" suppress-title="false" width="" alt="" title="" align="left">
                    <artwork height="" name="" width="" type="" alt="" align="left" xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[
HTTP/1.1 201 Created
Content-Type: application/json
Location: /User/3f62ce30-dcd6-4dd7-abfe-2352a76f9978

{
  "id" : "3f62ce30-dcd6-4dd7-abfe-2352a76f9978",
  "errors" : [ ],  //TODO - not in core schema
  "success" : true //TODO - not in core schema
}

                        ]]></artwork>
                </figure>


            </section>
            <section title="Retrieving Users" anchor="get-users-ops" toc="default">
                <t>Users may be retrieved via opaque, unique URIs or via Query</t>

                <section title="Retrieving a known User" anchor="get-user" toc="default">
                    <t>To retrieve a known User, clients send GET requests to the User endpoint /User/{id}.</t>

                    <t>If the User exists the server responds with a status code of 200 and includes the User in the
                        body of the response.
                    </t>

                    <section title="Example">
                        <figure height="" suppress-title="false" width="" alt="" title="" align="left">
                            <artwork height="" name="" width="" type="" alt="" align="left" xml:space="preserve">
                                <![CDATA[
GET /User/3f62ce30-dcd6-4dd7-abfe-2352a76f9978
Host: example.com
Accept: application/json
Authorization: Bearer h480djs93hd8

HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Type: application/json

                        ]]></artwork>
                        </figure>

                        <t>The server responds with:
                        </t>

                        <figure height="" suppress-title="false" width="" alt="" title="" align="left">
                            <artwork height="" name="" width="" type="" alt="" align="left" xml:space="preserve">
                                <![CDATA[

HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Type: application/json

{
  "schemas": ["urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0"],
  "id": "3f62ce30-dcd6-4dd7-abfe-2352a76f9978",
  "externalId": "701984",
  "userName": "bjensen@example.com",
  "name": {
    "formatted": "Ms. Barbara J Jensen III",
    "familyName": "Jensen",
    "givenName": "Barbara",
    "middleName": "Jane",
    "honorificPrefix": "Ms.",
    "honorificSuffix": "III"
  },
    "displayName": "Babs Jensen",
    "nickName": "Babs",
    "profileUrl": "https://login.example.org/bjensen",
    "emails": [
      {
        "value": "bjensen@example.com",
        "type": "work",
        "primary": true
      },
      {
        "value": "babs@jensen.org",
        "type": "home"
      }
    ],
    "meta": {
     "created": "2010-03-25T15:11:18Z",
     "lastModified": "2011-05-27T16:37:25Z"
  }
}


                        ]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </section>

                </section>

                <section title="Listing/Querying Users" anchor="query-users" toc="default">
                    <t>
                        SCIM defines a standard set of operations that can be used to filter, sort, and paginate
                        response results. The operations are specified by adding query parameter to the Users endpoint.
                        Service Providers MAY support additional query parameters not specified here, and Providers
                        SHOULD ignore any query parameters they don't recognize.
                    </t>

                    <figure height="" suppress-title="false" width="" alt="" title="" align="left">
                        <artwork height="" name="" width="" type="" alt="" align="left" xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[

GET /Users?attributes=userName,displayName
Host: example.com
Accept: application/json
Authorization: Bearer h480djs93hd8
                      ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>

                    <figure height="" suppress-title="false" width="" alt="" title="" align="left">
                        <artwork height="" name="" width="" type="" alt="" align="left" xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[

HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Type: application/json

{
  "totalResults": 3,
  "entry": [
    {
      "schemas": ["urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0"],
      "id": "3f62ce30-dcd6-4dd7-abfe-2352a76f9978",
      "displayName": "Babs Jensen",
      "userName": "bjensen",
      "meta": {
        "location":"/User/3f62ce30-..."
      }
    },
    {
      "schemas": ["urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0"],
      "id": "4f62ce30-dcd6-4dd7-abfe-2352a76f9978",
      "displayName": "Mandy Pepperidge",
      "userName": "mPepperidge",
      "meta": {
        "location":"/User/4f62ce30-..."
      }
    },
    {
      "schemas": ["urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0"],
      "id": "5f62ce30-dcd6-4dd7-abfe-2352a76f9978",
      "displayName": "Noel Smith",
      "userName": "nsmith",
      "meta": {
        "location":"/User/5f62ce30-..."
      }
    }
  ]
}
                      ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>


                    <section title="Filtering">
                        <t>
                            Filtering is used to limit the request results to Users that match given criteria. Content
                            filtering is accomplished by combining three request parameters:
                        </t>

                        <list style="hanging">
                            <t hangText="filterBy:">
                                Specifies the field name to filter by. If the specified field is a Plural Field, the
                                User SHALL match if any of the instances of the given field match the specified
                                criterion (e.g. if a contact has multiple emails values, only one has to match for the
                                entire User to match). If a Simple Field is specified, its value must match the
                                specified filterValue according to the specified filterOp. If a Complex Field is
                                specified, its Primary Sub-Field must match. If the specified field is not a direct
                                child of the entry element, the full path MUST be specified using the '.' character as
                                separator. For example, to filter by userName the parameter value is userName and to
                                filter by first name, the parameter value is name.givenName.
                            </t>
                            <t hangText="filterOp:">
                                Specifies the comparison method used to evaluate the field value with the value of the
                                filter criterion.

                                Providers SHOULD support the following values:

                                <list style="hanging">
                                    <t hangText="equals:">the two values must be identical strings. TODO: case
                                        sensitivity?
                                    </t>
                                    <t hangText="contains:">the entire filterValue must be a substring of the User field
                                        value.
                                    </t>
                                    <t hangText="startswith:">the entire filterValue must be a substring of the User
                                        field value, starting at the beginning of the field value. This criterion is
                                        satisfied if the two strings are equal.
                                    </t>
                                    <t hangText="present:">a User matches the criterion if the field specified by
                                        filterBy has a non-empty value, or if it contains a non-empty node for complex
                                        fields.
                                    </t>
                                </list>
                                Providers MAY support additional filter operations if they choose. Providers MUST
                                decline to filter results if the specified filter operation is not recognized

                            </t>

                            <t hangText="filterValue:">
                                Specifies the value to filter by, using the comparison method defined by filterOp. In
                                addition, requests can filter content based on their update timestamp: updatedSince:
                            </t>
                        </list>

                        <t>
                            Here are a few illustrative examples of filtering matches with filterBy, filterOp, and
                            filterValue. In each case, assume the following two Users would be returned if no filtering
                            parameters were provided:
                        </t>
                        <figure height="" suppress-title="false" width="" alt="" title="" align="left">
                            <artwork height="" name="" width="" type="" alt="" align="left" xml:space="preserve">
                                <![CDATA[
{
  "schemas": ["urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0"],
  "id": "3f62ce30-dcd6-4dd7-abfe-2352a76f9978",
  "externalId": "701984",
  "userName": "bjensen@example.com",
  "name": {
    "formatted": "Ms. Barbara J Jensen III",
  },
  "displayName": "Babs Jensen",
},
{
  "schemas": ["urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0"],
  "id": "4d31ce30-dcd6-4dd7-abfe-2352a76f8852",
  "externalId": "563471",
  "userName": "jsmith@example.org",
  "name": {
    "formatted": "Mr. John Smith",
  },
  "displayName": "John Smith"
  }
}

                        ]]></artwork>
                        </figure>

                        <t>
                            Given the parameters filterBy=displayName&amp;filterOp=startswith&amp;filterValue=Babs, only
                            the first User (with id=3f62ce30-dcd6-4dd7-abfe-2352a76f9978) would match and be returned.
                            However, with parameters filterBy=displayName&amp;filterOp=present, both contacts would be
                            returned. Given the parameters filterBy=email&amp;filterOp=contains&amp;filterValue=example.org,
                            only the second contact (with id=2) would match, as would it be the only contact to match
                            given the parameters filterBy=email&amp; filterOp=present.

                            If a request specifies a filterValue but no filterBy or filterOp, it is up to the Provider
                            how to interpret this filter request. Providers MAY choose to default to filtering by a
                            given field (e.g., displayName); they MAY choose to implement a custom, Provider-specific
                            query syntax for filterValue in this case; or they MAY choose to reject requests of this
                            type. In general, if Consumers want to request specific behavior from Providers, they should
                            do so by being explicit in their use of query parameters.
                        </t>
                    </section>

                    <section title="Sorting">
                        <t>Sorting allows requests to specify the order in which Users are returned.</t>

                        <list style="hanging">
                            <t hangText="sortBy:">
                                Specifies the field name whose value SHALL be used to order the returned Users. The sort
                                order is determine by the sortOrder parameter. If sortBy is a Singular Field, users are
                                sorted according to that field's value; if it's a Plural Field, Users are sorted by the
                                Value (or Major Value, if it's a Complex Field) of the field marked with "primary":
                                "true", if any, or else the first value in the list, if any, or else they are sorted
                                last if the given User has no data for the given field.
                            </t>

                            <t hangText="sortOrder:">
                                The order in which the sortBy parameter is applied. Allowed values are ascending and
                                descending. If a value for sortBy is provided and no sortOrder is specifies, the
                                sortOrder SHALL default to ascending. Sort order is expected to be case-insensitive
                                Unicode alphabetic sort order, with no specific locale implied.
                            </t>
                        </list>
                    </section>

                    <section title="Pagination">
                        <t>The pagination parameters can be used together to "page through" a large number of results in
                            manageable chunks
                        </t>

                        <list style="hanging">
                            <t hangText="startIndex:">
                                Specifies the offset of the first result to be returned with respect to the list of
                                Users that would be returned if no startIndex were provided. For instance, if in a given
                                request 10 Users would normally be provided, if startIndex is 7 and no count is
                                specified, then only the last 3 Users in that list would be returned (contacts are
                                zero-indexed). If startIndex is greater than or equal to the total number of results
                                that would be returned, no Users are returned. Value MUST be a non-negative integer and
                                defaults to 0 if no value is specified.
                            </t>

                            <t hangText="count:">
                                If non-zero, specifies the maximum number of Users the Consumer would like the Provider
                                to return at a time. Value MUST be a non-negative integer and defaults to 0 if no value
                                is specified. A count of 0 means that is up to the Provider to determine how many Users
                                to return by default (some Providers may return all Users by default; others may return
                                a fixed default number like 10). Providers SHOULD honor a very large count value, and
                                SHOULD support returning all Users at once when presented with a count request that is
                                larger than the number of Users the user has, but Providers MAY choose to never return
                                more than a Provider-determined maximum number of contacts per request, if returning all
                                Users is too burdensome. In all cases, at most count Users SHALL be returned, starting
                                at startIndex and counting up from there. In each of these cases, Providers MUST
                                indicate the total number of Users they chose to return in the response using the
                                itemsPerPage response element.
                            </t>
                        </list>
                        <t>
                            For instance, on an initial query, specifying startIndex=0&amp;count=10 will return only the
                            first 10 results. The total number of possible results is indicated by the totalResults
                            field of results, so the client knows how many "pages" of results exist. A subsequent query
                            of startIndex=10&amp;count=10 will return the next 10 results, and so on.
                        </t>
                    </section>

                </section>

                <section title="Additional retrieval query parameters" toc="default">
                    <t>
                        Clients MAY request a partial User representation by specifying an attributes query parameter
                        within the request URL. If non-empty, each User returned SHALL contain only the fields
                        explicitly requested. The server MAY return a subset of the requested fields if they are not
                        supported. This field is used for efficiency when the client only wishes to access a subset of
                        the fields normally returned in results. Value is a comma separated list of top level attribute
                        names (e.g. id,name,emails) and defaults to an empty list which means it's up to the Server
                        which fields to return.
                    </t>
                    <figure height="" suppress-title="false" width="" alt="" title="" align="left">
                        <artwork height="" name="" width="" type="" alt="" align="left" xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[
GET /User/3f62ce30-dcd6-4dd7-abfe-2352a76f9978?attributes=displayName
Host: example.com
Accept: application/json
Authorization: Bearer h480djs93hd8

HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Type: application/json

                    ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <t>Giving the response</t>

                    <figure height="" suppress-title="false" width="" alt="" title="" align="left">
                        <artwork height="" name="" width="" type="" alt="" align="left" xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[

HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Type: application/json

{
  "schemas": ["urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0"],
  "displayName": "Babs Jensen"
}

                        ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </section>
            </section>


            <section title="Editing a User" toc="default">
                <section title="Editing a User with PUT" anchor="edit-user-with-put" toc="default">
                    <t>
                        PUT performs a full User update. Consumers must retrieve the entire User and PUT the desired
                        User modifications.
                    </t>
                    <figure height="" suppress-title="false" width="" alt="" title="" align="left">
                        <artwork height="" name="" width="" type="" alt="" align="left" xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[
PUT /User/3f62ce30-dcd6-4dd7-abfe-2352a76f9978
Host: example.com
Accept: application/json
Authorization: Bearer h480djs93hd8

{
  "schemas": ["urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0"],
  "id": "3f62ce30-dcd6-4dd7-abfe-2352a76f9978",
  "externalId": "701984",
  "userName": "bjensen@example.com",
  "name": {
    "formatted": "Ms. Barbara J Jensen III",
    "familyName": "Jensen",
    "givenName": "Barbara",
    "middleName": "Jane",
    "honorificPrefix": "Ms.",
    "honorificSuffix": "III"
  },
  "displayName": "Barbara Jensen",
  "nickName": "Babs",
  "profileUrl": "https://login.example.org/bjensen",
  "emails": [
    {
      "value": "bjensen@example.com",
      "type": "work",
      "primary": true
    },
    {
    "value": "babs@jensen.org",
    "type": "home"
    }
  ]
}
                       ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <t>
                        The service responds with the entire, updated User
                    </t>
                    <figure height="" suppress-title="false" width="" alt="" title="" align="left">
                        <artwork height="" name="" width="" type="" alt="" align="left" xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[

HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Type: application/json

{
 "schemas": ["urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0", "http://hrextension/"],
  "id": "3f62ce30-dcd6-4dd7-abfe-2352a76f9978",
  "externalId": "701984",
  "userName": "bjensen@example.com",
  "name": {
   "formatted": "Ms. Barbara J Jensen III",
   "familyName": "Jensen",
   "givenName": "Barbara",
   "middleName": "Jane",
   "honorificPrefix": "Ms.",
   "honorificSuffix": "III"
 },
 "displayName": "Barbara Jensen",
 "nickName": "Babs",
 "profileUrl": "https://login.example.org/bjensen",
 "emails": [
   {
     "value": "bjensen@example.com",
     "type": "work",
     "primary": true
   },
   {
     "value": "babs@jensen.org",
     "type": "home"
   }
 ],
 "http://hrextension" : [
   {
     "gender": "female"
   },
   {
     "birthday": "1942-04-26"
   }
 ],
 "meta": {
   "created": "2010-03-25T15:11:18Z",
   "lastModified": "2011-05-27T16:37:25Z"
 }
}

               ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </section>

                <section title="Editing a User with PATCH" anchor="edit-user-with-patch" toc="default">
                    <t>PATCH enables consumers to send only those attributes requiring modification reducing network and
                        processing overhead. Attributes may be deleted, replaced or added in a single request.
                    </t>
                    <list style="hanging">
                        <t hangText="Deleting attribute values:">

                            Use the meta attribute to specify the attribute(s) to be deleted from the User. In the case
                            of plural attributes all attribute values will be deleted. The below request will delete the
                            “emails” attribute values.
                            <figure height="" suppress-title="false" width="" alt="" title="" align="left">
                                <artwork height="" name="" width="" type="" alt="" align="left" xml:space="preserve">
                                    <![CDATA[

{
  "meta": {
    "attributes": [
      "emails"
    ]
  }
}
                             ]]></artwork>
                            </figure>
                        </t>

                        <t hangText="Adding attributes (Singluar):">
                            If the User does not already contain a value for the specified attribute the attribute value
                            is added (or said another way “set”).
                        </t>

                        <t hangText="Adding attributes (Plural):">
                            If the User does not already contain the value the value is added to the attribute

                            <figure height="" suppress-title="false" width="" alt="" title="" align="left">
                                <artwork height="" name="" width="" type="" alt="" align="left" xml:space="preserve">
                                    <![CDATA[

PATCH /User/3f62ce30-dcd6-4dd7-abfe-2352a76f9978
Host: example.com
Accept: application/json
Authorization: Bearer h480djs93hd8

{
  "schemas": ["urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0"],
  "emails": [
    {
      "value": "babs@exmaple.org",
      "type": "home"
    }
  ]
}
]]></artwork>
                            </figure>
                        </t>


                        <t hangText="Updating attributes (Singular):">
                            If the attribute value already exists the value is replaced by the value specified in the
                            request.
                            <figure height="" suppress-title="false" width="" alt="" title="" align="left">
                                <artwork height="" name="" width="" type="" alt="" align="left" xml:space="preserve">
                                    <![CDATA[
PATCH /User/3f62ce30-dcd6-4dd7-abfe-2352a76f9978
Host: example.com
Accept: application/json
Authorization: Bearer h480djs93hd8

{
"schemas": ["urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0"],
"displayName":"Mrs Barbara Jensen"
}

Singular, complex attributes may be partially merged by specifying only those attributes intended
for update.

PATCH /User/3f62ce30-dcd6-4dd7-abfe-2352a76f9978
Host: example.com
Accept: application/json
Authorization: Bearer h480djs93hd8

{
"schemas": ["urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0"],
"name": {
  "familyName": "Smith"
  }
}
     ]]></artwork>
                            </figure>
                        </t>

                        <t hangText="Updating attributes (Plural):">


                            To replace the contents of a plural attribute specify the attribute name in the meta
                            attributes and specify all of the replacement attributes.

                            <figure height="" suppress-title="false" width="" alt="" title="" align="left">
                                <artwork height="" name="" width="" type="" alt="" align="left" xml:space="preserve">
                                    <![CDATA[
PATCH /User/3f62ce30-dcd6-4dd7-abfe-2352a76f9978
Host: example.com
Accept: application/json
Authorization: Bearer h480djs93hd8

{
  "schemas": ["urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0"],
  "emails": [
    {
      "value": "babs@exmaple.org",
      "type": "home"
    },
    {
      "value": "babswork@exmaple.org",
      "type": "work"
    }
  ],
  "meta": {
    "attributes": "emails"
  }
}
                         ]]></artwork>
                            </figure>
                        </t>

                    </list>

                    <section title="Additional query parameters" toc="default">
                        <t>
                            Consumers MAY request a partial User representation by specifying an attributes query
                            parameter within the request URL. If non-empty, each User returned SHALL contain only the
                            fields explicitly requested. The server MAY return a subset of the requested fields if they
                            are not supported. This field is used for efficiency when the client only wishes to access a
                            subset of the fields normally returned in results. Value is a comma separated list of top
                            level attribute names (e.g. id,name,emails) and defaults to an empty list which means it's
                            up to the Server which fields to return. For example:
                        </t>

                        <figure height="" suppress-title="false" width="" alt="" title="" align="left">
                            <artwork height="" name="" width="" type="" alt="" align="left" xml:space="preserve">
                                <![CDATA[
PATCH /User/3f62ce30-dcd6-4dd7-abfe-2352a76f9978?attributes=userName,displayName
                                    ]]></artwork>
                        </figure>

                    </section>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section title="Removing a User" anchor="delete-user" toc="default">
                <t>Consumers request User removal via DELETE. Service Providers MAY choose not to permenantly delete the
                    User, but MUST return a 404 error code for all PUT, PATCH, DELETE and GET operations with the User
                    id. Service Providers MUST also omit the User from query results.
                </t>
                <figure height="" suppress-title="false" width="" alt="" title="" align="left">
                    <artwork height="" name="" width="" type="" alt="" align="left" xml:space="preserve">
                        <![CDATA[

DELETE /User/3f62ce30-dcd6-4dd7-abfe-2352a76f9978
Host: example.com
Authorization: Bearer h480djs93hd8
                                      ]]></artwork>
                </figure>

                Server Response:
                <figure height="" suppress-title="false" width="" alt="" title="" align="left">
                    <artwork height="" name="" width="" type="" alt="" align="left" xml:space="preserve">
                        <![CDATA[
HTTP/1.1 200 OK
            ]]></artwork>
                </figure>


                <t>Example: Consumer attempt to retrieve the previously deleted User</t>
                <figure height="" suppress-title="false" width="" alt="" title="" align="left">
                    <artwork height="" name="" width="" type="" alt="" align="left" xml:space="preserve">
                        <![CDATA[

GET /User/3f62ce30-dcd6-4dd7-abfe-2352a76f9978
Host: example.com
Authorization: Bearer h480djs93hd8
                                      ]]></artwork>
                </figure>

                Server Response:
                <figure height="" suppress-title="false" width="" alt="" title="" align="left">
                    <artwork height="" name="" width="" type="" alt="" align="left" xml:space="preserve">
                        <![CDATA[
HTTP/1.1 404 NOT FOUND
            ]]></artwork>
                </figure>

            </section>
            <section title="Retrieving Service Provider Schema" anchor="schemas" toc="default">
                <t>Service Providers MUST support the core schema and MAY support additional schemas.</t>
                <section title="Retrieving a specific Schema" anchor="get-schema" toc="default">
                    <t>To retrieve schema send a GET request to /Schema/{resource}/{schema urn}.

                        Consumers may request the core User schema by omitting the schema URN; e.g.,/Schema/User/ or
                        specifying the core schema URN; e.g., /Schema/User/urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0
                    </t>
                    <figure height="" suppress-title="false" width="" alt="" title="" align="left">
                        <artwork height="" name="" width="" type="" alt="" align="left" xml:space="preserve">
                            <![CDATA[

GET /Schema/User
Host: example.com
Accept: application/json
Authorization: Bearer h480djs93hd8
            ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>

                    Server Response:

                    <figure height="" suppress-title="false" width="" alt="" title="" align="left">
                        <artwork height="" name="" width="" type="" alt="" align="left" xml:space="preserve">
                            <![CDATA[
HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Type: application/json

TBD

            ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>

                </section>

                <section title="Retrieving all Service Provider supported Schemas" anchor="get-schemas" toc="default">
                    <t>Consumers may request all supported schemas for a given resource via /Schemas/{resource}</t>


                    <figure height="" suppress-title="false" width="" alt="" title="" align="left">
                        <artwork height="" name="" width="" type="" alt="" align="left" xml:space="preserve">
                            <![CDATA[

GET /Schemas/User
Host: example.com
Accept: application/json
Authorization: Bearer h480djs93hd8
                ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>

                    Server Response:

                    <figure height="" suppress-title="false" width="" alt="" title="" align="left">
                        <artwork height="" name="" width="" type="" alt="" align="left" xml:space="preserve">
                            <![CDATA[
HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Type: application/json

{
  "totalResults": 2,
  "entry": [
    {
      "name": "Core",
      "urn": "urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0",
      "description": "SCIM Core 1.0 User Schema",
      "meta": {
        "location":"/Schema/User/urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0"
      }
    },
    {
      "name": "HR",
      "urn": "http://hrextension/",
      "description": "SCIM HR extension",
      "meta": {
        "location":"/Schema/User/http://hrextension"
      }
    }
  ]
}

                ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>


                </section>
            </section>


            <section title="Data Input/Output Formats" anchor="io-format">
                <t>
                    Consumers SHOULD specify the format in which the data is submitted and MAY specify the desired
                    response data format. Consumers MAY indicate the desired format via an HTTP Accept Header;
                    e.g.,"Accept: application/json" or via URI suffix; e.g.,

                    <figure height="" suppress-title="false" width="" alt="" title="" align="left">
                        <artwork height="" name="" width="" type="" alt="" align="left" xml:space="preserve">
                            <![CDATA[
GET /User/3f62ce30-dcd6-4dd7-abfe-2352a76f9978.json
Host: example.com

GET /User/3f62ce30-dcd6-4dd7-abfe-2352a76f9978.xml
Host: example.com
            ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>

                </t>

                <t>
                    Service Providers MUST support the Accept Headers "Accept: application/json" for
                    <eref target="http://json.org">JSON</eref>
                    and "Accept: application/xml" for
                    <eref target="http://www.w3.org/XML/">XML</eref>
                    and MAY support additional formats if desired. The format defaults to json if no format is
                    specified. The data structure returned is equivalent in both formats; the only difference is in the
                    encoding of the data. Singular Fields are encoded as string key/value pairs in JSON and tags with
                    text content in XML, e.g. "field": "value" and
                    <field>value</field>
                    respectively. Plural Fields and Plural Bundles are encoded as arrays in JSON and repeated tags in
                    XML, e.g. "fields": [ "value1", "value2" ] and
                    <fields>value1</fields>
                    <fields>value2</fields>
                    respectively. Nodes with multiple sub-nodes are represented as objects in JSON and tags with
                    sub-tags in XML, e.g. "field": { "subfield1": "value1", "subfield2": "value2" } and
                    <field>
                        <subfield1>value1</subfield1>
                        <subfield2>value2</subfield2>
                    </field>
                    respectively.
                </t>
            </section>

            <section title="HTTP Response Codes">
                <t>
                    The SCIM Protocol uses the response status codes defined in HTTP to indicate operation success or
                    failure. Refer to the HTTP specification for <eref
                        target="http://www.w3.org/Protocols/rfc2616/rfc2616-sec10.html">status code descriptions</eref>.
                    Implementers SHOULD, per the HTTP specification, return human-readable explanations for HTTP 4xx and
                    5xx responses.
                </t>
            </section>


            <section title="HTTP Method Overloading">
                <t>In recognition that some clients, servers and firewalls prevent PUT, PATCH and DELETE operations a
                    client MAY override the POST operation by specifying the custom header "X-HTTP-Method-Override" with
                    the intended PUT, PATCH, DELETE operation. For example:
                </t>
                <figure height="" suppress-title="false" width="" alt="" title="" align="left">
                    <artwork height="" name="" width="" type="" alt="" align="left" xml:space="preserve">
                        <![CDATA[
POST /User/3f62ce30-dcd6-4dd7-abfe-2352a76f9978
X-HTTP-Method-Override: DELETE
]]></artwork>
                </figure>

            </section>

        </section>
        <section title="Todos">
            <list style="numbers">
                <t>Relative or Absolute URLS for Location header and embedded meta tag</t>
                <t>Additional Endpoints: Groups e.g., /Group(s) If so change user 'groups' semantics to 'memberOf')?
                </t>

                <t>Change password; e.g., /ChangePassword</t>
                <t>Endpoint extension"Via extension a la schema e.g., /Device, /Service
                </t>
                <t>Data consistency semantics - Suggest etag</t>
                <t>Binary Data handling. Suggest encode as base64. Need to jive with Schema, should provide api way to skip binary attrs?</t>

            </list>
        </section>


        <section title="Acknowledgments">
          <t>Portable Contacts - <eref target="http://www.portablecontacts.net/draft-spec.html" type="HTML">Portable Contacts 1.0 Draft C</eref></t>
        </section>

    </middle>

    <back>
    </back>
</rfc>