<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-scim-core-schema-01" ipr="trust200902">
  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>

  <?rfc tocdepth="2" ?>

  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>

  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

  <?rfc strict="no" ?>

  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>

  <?rfc private="Draft" ?>

  <front>
    <title abbrev="scim-core-schema-01">Simple Cloud Identity Management: Core
    Schema 1.0 - draft 1</title>

    <author fullname="Chuck Mortimore" initials="C." role="editor"
            surname="Mortimore">
      <organization abbrev="Salesforce">Salesforce.com</organization>

      <address>
        <email>cmortimore@salesforce.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Patrick Harding" initials="P." surname="Harding">
      <organization abbrev="Ping">Ping Identity</organization>

      <address>
        <email>pharding@pingidentity.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Paul Madsen" initials="P." surname="Madsen">
      <organization abbrev="Ping">Ping Identity</organization>

      <address>
        <email>pmadsen@pingidentity.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Joseph Smarr" initials="J." surname="Smarr">
      <organization abbrev="Google">Google</organization>

      <address>
        <email>jsmarr@google.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="13" month="June" year="2011" />

    <abstract>
      <t>The Simple Cloud Identity Management (SCIM) specification is designed
      to make managing user identity in cloud based applications and services
      easier. The specification suite seeks to build upon experience with
      existing schemas and deployments, placing specific emphasis on
      simplicity of development and integration, while applying existing
      authentication, authorization, and privacy models. Its intent is to
      reduce the cost and complexity of user management operations by
      providing a common user schema and extension model, as well as binding
      documents to provide patterns for exchanging this schema using standard
      protocols. In essence, make it fast, cheap, and easy to move users in
      to, out of, and around the cloud.</t>

      <t>This document provides a platform neutral schema and extension model
      for representing users and groups. This schema is intended for exchange
      and use with cloud service providers. Standard serializations of that
      schema using JSON and XML are also provided.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="rnc" title="Requirements Notation and Conventions">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119" />
      .</t>

      <t>Throughout this document, values are quoted to indicate that they are
      to be taken literally. When using these values in protocol messages, the
      quotes MUST NOT be used as part of the value.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="overview" title="Overview">
      <t>While there are existing standards for describing and exchanging user
      information, many of these standards can be difficult to implement
      and/or use wire protocols that do not easily traverse firewalls nor
      easily layer onto existing web protocols. As a result, many cloud
      providers provide their own non-standard APIs for managing users within
      their services. This increases both the cost and complexity associated
      with organizations adopting products and services from multiple cloud
      providers as they must perform redundant integration development.
      Similarly, cloud services providers seeking to interoperate with
      multiple application marketplaces or cloud identity providers must be
      redundantly integrated.</t>

      <t>SCIM seeks to simplify this problem through a simple to implement
      specification suite that provides a common user schema and extension
      model, as well as binding documents to provide patterns for exchanging
      this schema using standard protocols. It draws inspiration and best
      practice, building upon existing user APIs and schemas from a wide
      variety of sources including, but not limited to, existing APIs exposed
      by cloud providers, PortableContacts, and LDAP directory services.</t>

      <t>This document provides a platform neutral schema and extension model
      for representing users and groups. This schemas is intended for exchange
      and use with cloud service providers.Standard serializations of that
      schema using JSON and XML are also provided. Additional binding
      documents provide a standard REST API, as well as use of SCIM schema
      over federation protocols such as SAML and OpenID</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="schema_structure" title="SCIM Schema Structure">
      <t>SCIM schema provides a minimal core schema for representing users and
      groups, encompassing common attributes found in many existing deployments
      and schemas.</t>

      <t>Each attribute is defined as either a Singular Attribute, in which
      case there MUST NOT be more than one instance of that field per user, or
      as a Plural Attribute, in which case any number of instances of that
      attribute MAY be present per user. The only exception to this is a
      "schemas" attribute used in representations that lack native support for
      expressing schemas such as JSON. This attribute allows introspection of
      the supported schema version for a SCIM representation as well any
      schema extensions supported by that representation. The 'schemas'
      attribute is an array of strings, and values must be URNs designated by
      the corresponding schema definition.</t>

      <t>SCIM information is formatted using labeled attributes with either
      structured or unstructured string data. Unless otherwise specified, all
      attributes are optional and of type xs:string. All encoding MUST be
      UTF-8. Each attribute label uses camelCase notation. Unless specified,
      all attribute values MUST NOT contain any newline characters (\r or
      \n).</t>

      <t>Each attribute value consists of one of the following types:</t>

      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Simple">A single string attribute which MAY specify a
          REQUIRED data format or allow any string. A simple attribute MAY
          contain Canonical Values specified, in which case Service Providers
          SHOULD conform to those values if appropriate, but MAY
          provide alternate string values to represent additional values.</t>

          <t hangText="Complex">A multi-value attribute containing any
          combination of other attributes. Complex attributes are defined by
          listing the child attributes and their types. For most Complex
          Attributes, the value sub-attribute contains the Major Value of that
          attribute (i.e. the primary piece of information described by that
          attribute), and the other attributes provide additional
          meta-data.</t>

          <t hangText="Boolean">A special case of a Simple Attribute with two
          legal values: true and false. Values are case-sensitive.</t>

          <t hangText="DateTime">The attribute value MUST be a valid
          xsd:dateTime (e.g. 2008-01-23T04:56:22Z) value as specified in
            <eref target="http://www.w3.org/TR/xmlschema-2/#dateTime">
               section 3.2.7 of the XML Schema Datatypes Specification
              </eref>.
          </t>

          <t hangText="Binary">The attribute value MUST be encoded as a valid
          xsd:base64Binary value as specified in <eref target="http://www.w3.org/TR/xmlschema-2/#base64Binary"> section 3.2.16 of the XML Schema
              Datatypes Specification</eref>.  No binary attributes
            are specified in the core schema, however,
            extended schemas may opt to include images,
            digital signatures, and the like.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>Plural Attributes allow for lists of attributes using a special
      complex type. All Plural Attributes, unless otherwise specified, have
      the same three standard sub-attributes:</t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="value">The primary value of this attribute, e.g. the
          actual e-mail address, phone number, ID, URL, etc. Each non-empty
          Plural Attribute value MUST contain at least the value
          sub-attribute, but all other sub-attributes are optional.
          REQUIRED.</t>

          <t hangText="type">The type of attribute for this instance, usually
          used to label the preferred function of the given resource.
          OPTIONAL</t>

          <t hangText="primary">A Boolean value indicating whether this
          instance of the Plural Attribute is the primary or preferred value
          of for this attribute, e.g. the preferred mailing address or primary
          e-mail address. Service Providers MUST NOT mark more than one
          instance of the same Plural Attribute as primary, and MAY choose not
          to mark any attributes as primary, if this information is not
          available. For efficiency, Service Providers SHOULD NOT mark all
          non-primary attributes with primary="false", but should instead omit
          this sub-attribute for all non-primary instances. OPTIONAL</t>

          <t hangText="display">A human readable name, primarily used for
          display purposes where the value is an opaque or complex type such
          as an id. READ-ONLY and OPTIONAL.</t>

          <t hangText="operation">The operation to perform on the plural attribute during a PATCH request. The only
              valid value is "delete", which signifies that the attribute should be removed
              from the Resource. OPTIONAL.</t>

        </list>When returning Plural Attributes, Service Providers SHOULD
      canonicalize the value returned, if appropriate (e.g. for e-mail
      addresses and URLs). Providers MAY return the same value more than once
      with different types (e.g. the same e-mail address may used for work and
      home), but SHOULD NOT return the same (type, value) combination more
      than once per Plural Attribute, as this complicates processing by the
      Consumer.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Schema Extension Model">
      <t>SCIM schema follows an object extension model similar to
      ObjectClasses used in LDAP. Unlike LDAP there is no inheritance model;
      all extensions are additive (similar to <eref target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4512">LDAP Auxiliary Object Classes</eref>). Each
      value indicates additive schema that may exist in a SCIM representation
      as specified by extensions not defined in this suite. Each schema
      extension must identify a canonical URI used to identify the extension.
      Schema Extensions MUST follow the rules of Singular and Plural Attribute
      structures defined in this core schema specification. Schema extensions
      MUST NOT override or redefine any schema defined in this core
      specification. For representations that support expressing schema, the
      native convention MUST be used (For instance, XML Namespace). When the
      the "schemas" attribute is being used (as defined in Section 5.2),
      additional URIs MUST be specified in the "schemas" attribute array.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="schema" title="SCIM Core Schema">
      <section title="Common Schema Attributes">
        <t>Each SCIM Resource (Users, Groups, etc.) implicitly
        includes the following common attributes. These common attributes MUST
        be included in all Resources, including any new Resource types
        that may be defined. It it not necessary to designate support for Core
        Schema with a value in the "schemas" attributes (defined in the next
        section), as inclusion is implicit and mandatory.</t>

        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="id">Unique identifier for the SCIM Resource as
            defined by the Service Provider. Each representation of the
            Resource MUST include a non-empty id value. This identifier MUST
            be unique across the Service Provider's entire set of Resources.
            It MUST be a stable, non-reassignable identifier that does not
            change when the same Resource is returned in subsequent requests.
            The value of the id attribute is always issued by the Service
            Provider and MUST never be specified by the Service Consumer.
            REQUIRED.</t>

         <t hangText="externalId">Unique identifier for the Resource as defined
            by the Service Consumer. The externalId may simplify
            identification of the Resource between Service Consumer and Service
            provider by allowing the Consumer to refer to the Resource with its
            own identifier, obviating the need to store a local mapping
            between the local identifier of the Resource and the identifier used
            by the Service Provider. Each Resource MAY include a non-empty
            externalId value. The value of the externalId attribute is always
            issued be the Service Consumer and can never be specified by the
            Service Provider. This identifier MUST be unique across the
            Service Consumer's entire set of Resources. It MUST be a stable,
            non-reassignable identifier that does not change when the same
            Resource is returned in subsequent requests. The Service Provider MUST
            always interpret the externalId as scoped to the Service
            Consumer's tenant. OPTIONAL.</t>

         <t hangText="meta">A complex type containing metadata about the
            resource. OPTIONAL.<list style="hanging">
                <t hangText="created">The DateTime the Resource was added to
                the Service Provider. The attribute MUST be a DateTime.
                READ-ONLY and OPTIONAL.</t>

                <t hangText="lastModified">The most recent DateTime the
                details of this Resource were updated at the Service Provider. If
                this Resource has never been modified since its initial creation,
                the value MUST be the same as the value of created. The
                attribute MUST be a DateTime. READ-ONLY and OPTIONAL.</t>

                <t hangText="location">The URI of the Resource being returned. This value MUST be the same as the
                    Location HTTP response header. READ-ONLY and OPTIONAL.</t>

                 <t hangText="version">The version of the Resource being returned. This value must be the same as the
                     ETag HTTP response header. READ-ONLY and OPTIONAL.</t>

                 <t hangText="attributes">The names of the attributes to remove from the Resource during a
                     PATCH operation. OPTIONAL.</t>
              </list></t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="&quot;schemas&quot; Attribute">
        <t>SCIM supports resources of different types, with extensible
        schemas. Each resource MUST be indicated using fully
        qualified URNs</t>

        <t>Where a specific representation has existing support for expressing
        schema, the traditional convention of that representation MUST be
        applied. For example, when representing users using XML, XML Namespace
        should be used.</t>

        <t>When a representation does not explicitly provide support for
        indicating a schema, such as JSON, a "schemas" attribute is used to
        indicate the version of SCIM schema as well as any schema
        extensions.</t>

        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="schemas">The schemas attribute is an array of strings
            which allows introspection of the supported schema version for a
            SCIM representation as well any schema extensions supported by
            that representation. Each string value must be a unique URN. This
            specification defines URNs for User, Group, and some standard
            extensions. All representations of SCIM schema MUST include a
            non-zero value array with value(s) of the URNs supported by that
            representation.  Duplicate values MUST NOT be included.  Value
            order is not specified and MUST not impact behavior. REQUIRED.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="SCIM User Schema">
      <t>SCIM provides a schema for representing Users, identified using the
      following URN: 'urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0' (Note: we're currently
      using an un-registered urn while in draft form). The following
      attributes are defined in addition to those attributes defined in Core
      SCIM Schema:</t>

      <section title="Singular Attributes">
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="userName">Unique identifier for the User, typically
            used by the user to directly authenticate to the service provider.
            Often displayed to the user as their unique identifier within the
            system (as opposed to id or externalId, which are generally
            opaque and not user-friendly identifiers). Each User MUST include
            a non-empty userName value. This identifier MUST be unique across
            the Service Consumer's entire set of Users. It MUST be a stable ID
            that does not change when the same User is returned in subsequent
            requests. REQUIRED.</t>



            <t hangText="name">The components of the User's real name.
            Providers MAY return just the full name as a single string in the
            formatted sub-attribute, or they MAY return just the individual
            component attributes using the other sub-attributes, or they MAY
            return both. If both variants are returned, they SHOULD be
            describing the same name, with the formatted name indicating how
            the component attributes should be combined. OPTIONAL.<list
                style="hanging">
                <t hangText="formatted">The full name, including all middle
                names, titles, and suffixes as appropriate, formatted for
                display (e.g. Ms. Barbara Jane Jensen, III.). OPTIONAL.</t>

                <t hangText="familyName">The family name of the User, or "Last
                Name" in most Western languages (e.g. Jensen given the full
                name Ms. Barbara Jane Jensen, III.). OPTIONAL.</t>

                <t hangText="givenName">The given name of the User, or "First
                Name" in most Western languages (e.g. Barbara given the full
                name Ms. Barbara Jane Jensen, III.). OPTIONAL.</t>

                <t hangText="middleName">The middle name(s) of the User (e.g.
                Robert given the full name Ms. Barbara Jane Jensen, III.).
                OPTIONAL.</t>

                <t hangText="honorificPrefix">The honorific prefix(es) of the
                User, or "Title" in most Western languages (e.g. Ms. given the
                full name Ms. Barbara Jane Jensen, III.). OPTIONAL.</t>

                <t hangText="honorificSuffix">The honorific suffix(es) of the
                User, or "Suffix" in most Western languages (e.g. III. given
                the full name Ms. Barbara Jane Jensen, III.). OPTIONAL.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t hangText="displayName">The name of the User, suitable for
            display to end-users. Each User returned MAY include a non-empty
            displayName value. The name SHOULD be the full name of the User
            being described if known (e.g. Babs Jensen or Ms. Barbara J
            Jensen, III), but MAY be a username or handle, if that is all that
            is available (e.g. bjensen). The value provided SHOULD be the
            primary textual label by which this User is normally displayed by
            the Service Provider when presenting it to end-users. OPTIONAL</t>

            <t hangText="nickName">The casual way to address the user in real
            life, e.g. "Bob" or "Bobby" instead of "Robert". This attribute
            SHOULD NOT be used to represent a User's username (e.g. bjensen or
            mpepperidge). OPTIONAL.</t>

            <t hangText="profileUrl">URL to a page representing the User's
            online profile. OPTIONAL.</t>

            <t hangText="title">The user&rsquo;s title, such as &ldquo;Vice
            President.&rdquo; OPTIONAL.</t>

            <t hangText="userType">Used to identify the organization to user
            relationship. Typical values used might be "Contractor",
            "Employee", "Intern", "Temp", "External", and "Unknown" but any
            value may be used. OPTIONAL.</t>

            <t hangText="preferredLanguage">Used to indicate a User's
            preferred written or spoken language. Generally used for
            localizing the interface presented to the user. OPTIONAL. TODO -
            what ISO code list should we use here?</t>

            <t hangText="locale">Used to indicate the User's default location
            for purposes of localizing items such as currency, date time
            format, numerical representations, etc. OPTIONAL. TODO - what ISO
            code list should we use here?</t>

            <t hangText="timezone">The User's time zone in the public-domain
              time zone database format; e.g.,'America/Denver'. Valid values
              and details at  <eref target="http://cs.ucla.edu/~eggert/tz/tz-link.htm">
               http://cs.ucla.edu/~eggert/tz/tz-link.htm
              </eref>.
              OPTIONAL.
            </t>
            <t hangText="active">A Boolean value indicating the User's administrative status. The definitive meaning of
                this attribute is determined by the Service Provider though a value of true infers the User is, for
                example, able to login while a value of false implies the User's account has been suspended.  OPTIONAL.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Plural Attributes">
        <t>The following Plural Attributes are defined:</t>

        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="emails">E-mail addresses for the User. The value
            SHOULD be canonicalized by the Service Provider, e.g.
            bjensen@example.com instead of bjensen@EXAMPLE.COM. Canonical Type
            values of work, home, and other. OPTIONAL.</t>

            <t hangText="phoneNumbers">Phone numbers for the User. No
            canonical value is assumed here. Canonical Type values of work,
            home, mobile, fax, pager and other. OPTIONAL.</t>

            <t hangText="ims">Instant messaging address for the User. No
            official canonicalization rules exist for all instant messaging
            addresses, but Service Providers SHOULD, when appropriate, remove all whitespace and
            convert the address to lowercase. Instead of the standard
            Canonical Values for type, this attribute defines the following
            Canonical Values to represent currently popular IM services: aim,
            gtalk, icq, xmpp, msn, skype, qq, and yahoo. OPTIONAL.</t>

            <t hangText="photos">URL of a photo of the User. The value SHOULD
            be a canonicalized URL, and MUST point to an image file
            (e.g. a GIF, JPEG, or PNG image file) rather than to a web page
            containing an image. Service Providers MAY return the same image
            at different sizes, though it is recognized that no standard for
            describing images of various sizes currently exists. Note that
            this attribute SHOULD NOT be used to send down arbitrary photos
            taken by this User, but specifically profile photos of the User
            suitable for display when describing the User. Instead of the
            standard Canonical Values for type, this attribute defines the
            following Canonical Values to represent popular photo sizes:
            photo, thumbnail. OPTIONAL.</t>

            <t hangText="addresses">A physical mailing address for this User. Canonical Type Values of work,
            home, and other. The value attribute is a complex type with the
            following sub-attributes. OPTIONAL <list style="hanging">
                <t hangText="formatted">The full mailing address, formatted
                for display or use with a mailing label. This attribute MAY
                contain newlines. OPTIONAL</t>

                <t hangText="streetAddress">The full street address component,
                which may include house number, street name, P.O. box, and
                multi-line extended street address information. This attribute
                MAY contain newlines. OPTIONAL</t>

                <t hangText="locality">The city or locality component.
                OPTIONAL</t>

                <t hangText="region">The state or region component.
                OPTIONAL</t>

                <t hangText="postalCode">The zipcode or postal code component.
                OPTIONAL</t>

                <t hangText="country">The country name component.
                  When specified the value MUST be in
                    <eref target="http://www.iso.org/iso/country_codes/iso_3166_code_lists/country_names_and_code_elements.htm">
                  ISO 3166-1 alpha 2 "short" code format</eref>; e.g., the United States and Sweden are "US" and "SE",
                  respectively.  OPTIONAL.
                </t>
              </list>
            </t>

            <t hangText="groups">A list of groups that the user belongs to.
              The values are meant to enable expression of common group or role
              based access control models, although no explicit authorization
              model is defined. It is intended that the semantics of group
              membership and any behavior or authorization granted as a result
              of membership are defined by the Service Provider are considered
              out of scope for this specification. This value has NO canonical
              types and removes the standard canonical types. If the SCIM
              Service Provider exposes a Group resource, the value MUST be the
              "id" attribute of the corresponding Group resources to which the
              user belongs.  OPTIONAL.
            </t>

            <t hangText="entitlements">A list of entitlements for the User that
              represent a thing the User has. That is, an entitlement is an
              additional right to a thing, object or service. No vocabulary or
              syntax is specified and Service Providers/Consumers are expected
              to encode sufficient information in the value so as to accurately
              and without ambiguity determine what the User has access to. This
              value has NO canonical types though type may be useful as a means
              to scope entitlements. OPTIONAL.
            </t>

            <t hangText="roles">A list of roles for the User that collectively
              represent who the User is; e.g., 'Student', "Faculty". No
              vocabulary or syntax is specified though it is expected that a
              role value is a string or label representing a collection of
              entitlements.  This value has NO canonical types and removes the
              standard canonical types.  OPTIONAL.
            </t>

          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="SCIM Enterprise User Schema Extension">
      <t>The following SCIM extension defines attributes commonly used in
      representing users that belong to, or act on behalf of a business or
      enterprise. The enterprise user extension is identified using the
      following URI: 'urn:scim:schemas:extension:user:enterprise:1.0' ( Note:
      we're currently using an un-registered urn while in draft form).</t>

      <t>The following Singular Attributes are defined:</t>

      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="employeeNumber">Numeric or alphanumeric identifier
          assigned to a person, typically based on order of hire or
          association with an organization. OPTIONAL.</t>

          <t hangText="costCenter">Identifies the name of a cost center.
          OPTIONAL.</t>

          <t hangText="organization">Identifies the name of an organization.
          OPTIONAL.</t>

          <t hangText="division">Identifies the name of a division.
          OPTIONAL.</t>

          <t hangText="department">Identifies the name of a department.
          OPTIONAL.</t>

          <t hangText="manager">The User's manager. A complex type that
          optionally allows Service Providers to represent organizational
          hierarchy by referencing the "id" attribute of another User.
          OPTIONAL<list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="managerId">The id of the SCIM resource representing
              the User's manager. OPTIONAL.</t>

              <t hangText="displayName">The displayName of the
                User's manager.  READ-ONLY and OPTIONAL.</t>
            </list></t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="SCIM Group Schema">
      <t>SCIM provides a schema for representing groups, identified using the
      following URN: 'urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0' ( Note: we're currently
      using an un-registered urn while in draft form).</t>

      <t>Group resources are meant to enable expression of common Group or
      role based access control models, although no explicit authorization
      model is defined. It is intended that the semantics of group membership
      and any behavior or authorization granted as a result of membership are
      defined by the Service Provider are considered out of scope for this
      specification.</t>

      <t>The following Singular Attribute is defined in addition to the common
      attributes defined in SCIM Core Schema:<list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="displayName">A human readable name for the Group.
          OPTIONAL.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t />

      <t>The following Plural Attribute is defined in addition to the common
      attributes defined in SCIM Core Schema:<list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="members">A list of members of the Group. Canonical Type "User" and "Group" are READ-ONLY. The
              value must be the "id" of a SCIM resource, either a User, or a Group. The intention of the Group type is
              to allow the Service Provider to support nested Groups. REQUIRED.
          </t>
        </list></t>

      <t />
    </section>


    <section title="Service Provider Configuration Schema">
      <t>SCIM provides a schema for representing the Service Provider's configuration identified using the
      following URN: 'urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0' ( Note: we're currently
      using an un-registered urn while in draft form).</t>

      <t>The Service Provider Configuration Resource enables a Service Provider to expose its compliance with the SCIM
          specification in a standardized form as well as provide additional implementation details to Consumers.
      </t>

      <t>The following Singular Attributes are defined in addition to the common attributes defined in Core Schema:
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="documentationUrl">An HTTP addressable URL pointing to the Service Provider's human consumable
              help documentation.  OPTIONAL.</t>
            <t hangText="patch">A complex type that specifies PATCH configuration options.  REQUIRED.
                <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="supported">Boolean value specifying whether the operation is supported. REQUIRED.</t>
                </list>
            </t>
            <t hangText="bulk">A complex type that specifies BULK configuration options.  REQUIRED.
                <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="supported">Boolean value specifying whether the operation is supported. REQUIRED.</t>
                </list>
                <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="maxResources">An integer value specifying the maximum number of Resources. REQUIRED.</t>
                </list>
                <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="maxPayloadSize">An integer value specifying the maximum payload size. REQUIRED.</t>
                </list>
            </t>
              <t hangText="filter">A complex type that specifies FILTER options.  REQUIRED.
                  <list style="hanging">
                      <t hangText="supported">Boolean value specifying whether the operation is supported. REQUIRED.</t>
                      <t hangText="maxResults">Integer value specifying the maximum number of Resources returned in a response. REQUIRED.</t>
                  </list>
              </t>
              <t hangText="changePassword">A complex type that specifies Change Password configuration options.  REQUIRED.
                  <list style="hanging">
                      <t hangText="supported">Boolean value specifying whether the operation is supported. REQUIRED.</t>
                  </list>
              </t>
              <t hangText="sort">A complex type that specifies Sort configuration options.  REQUIRED.
                  <list style="hanging">
                      <t hangText="supported">Boolean value specifying whether sorting is supported. REQUIRED.</t>
                  </list>
              </t>
              <t hangText="etag">A complex type that specifies Etag configuration options.  REQUIRED.
                  <list style="hanging">
                      <t hangText="supported">Boolean value specifying whether the operation is supported. REQUIRED.</t>
                  </list>
              </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>The following Plural Attribute is defined in addition to the common attributes defined in Core Schema:
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="authenticationSchemes">A complex type that specifies supported Authentication Scheme
            properties.  Instead of the standard Canonical Values for type, this attribute defines the
            following Canonical Values to represent common schemes: OAuth, OAuth2, HttpBasic, and HttpDigest.
            REQUIRED.
            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="name">The common authentication scheme name; e.g., HTTP Basic. REQUIRED.</t>
              <t hangText="description">A description of the Authentication Scheme. REQUIRED.</t>
              <t hangText="specUrl">A HTTP addressable URL pointing to the Authentication Scheme's
                specification.  OPTIONAL.
              </t>
              <t hangText="documentationUrl">A HTTP addressable URL pointing to the Authentication Scheme's
                usage documentation. OPTIONAL.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

      <section title="Resource Schema">
        <t>The Resource schema specifies the Attribute(s) and meta-data that constitute a Resource. Schema Resources
           are READ-ONLY and identified using the following URN: 'urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0' (Note: we're currently
           using an un-registered urn while in draft form).  Unlike other core Resources the schema Resource MAY contain
           a complex object within a Sub-Attribute.
        </t>
        <t>The following Singular Attributes are defined in addition to the common attributes defined in SCIM Core Schema:
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="name">The addressable Resource endpoint name.  When applicable Service Providers MUST specify the name specified in the core schema specification; e.g., "User" or "Group". REQUIRED.</t>
            <t hangText="description">The Resource's human readable description. When applicable Service Providers MUST specify the description specified in the core schema specification.  REQUIRED.</t>
            <t hangText="schema">The Resource's associated schema URN; e.g., urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0.  REQUIRED.</t>
            <t hangText="queryEndpoint">The Resource's HTTP addressable endpoint relative to the Base URL; e.g., /Users.  REQUIRED.</t>
           </list>
        </t>
          <t>The following Plural Attribute is defined in addition to the common attributes defined in SCIM Core Schema:
              <list style="hanging">
                  <t hangText="attributes">A complex type that specifies the set of associated Resource attributes.
                      REQUIRED.
                      <list style="hanging">
                          <t hangText="name">The attribute's name. REQUIRED.</t>
                          <t hangText="type">The attribute's data type; e.g., string. REQUIRED.</t>
                          <t hangText="plural">Specifies if the attribute is a plural. REQUIRED.</t>
                          <t hangText="description">The attribute's human readable description. When applicable Service
                              Providers MUST specify the description specified in the core schema specification.
                              REQUIRED.
                          </t>
                          <t hangText="schema">The attribute's associated schema; e.g., urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0.
                              REQUIRED.
                          </t>
                          <t hangText="readOnly">A Boolean value that specifies if the attribute is mutable. REQUIRED.
                          </t>
                          <t hangText="required">A Boolean value that specifies if the attribute is required. REQUIRED.
                          </t>
                          <t hangText="caseExact">A Boolean value that specifies if the string attribute is case
                              sensitive.
                              REQUIRED.
                          </t>
                          <t/>
                          <t>The following Plural Attributes are defined. There are no canonical type values defined
                            and the primary value serves no useful purpose.
                            <list style="hanging">
                              <t hangText="subAttributes">A list specifying the contained attributes. OPTIONAL.
                                <list style="hanging">
                                  <t hangText="name">The attribute's name. REQUIRED.</t>
                                  <t hangText="type">The attribute's data type; e.g., string. REQUIRED.</t>
                                  <t hangText="description">The attribute's human readable description. When
                                    applicable Service Providers MUST specify the description specified in the core
                                    schema specification. REQUIRED.
                                  </t>
                                  <t hangText="readOnly">A Boolean value that specifies if the attribute is mutable.
                                    REQUIRED.
                                  </t>
                                  <t hangText="required">A Boolean value that specifies if the attribute is required.
                                    REQUIRED.
                                  </t>
                                  <t hangText="caseExact">A Boolean value that specifies if the string attribute
                                    is case sensitive. REQUIRED.
                                  </t>
                                </list>
                              </t>
                              <t hangText="pluralTypes">A list of canonical type values. When
                                applicable Service Providers MUST specify the canonical types specified in the
                                core schema specification; e.g.,"work","home". OPTIONAL.
                              </t>
                            </list>
                          </t>
                      </list>
                  </t>
              </list>
          </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="json_representation" title="JSON Representation">
      <section title="Minimal User Representation">
        <t>The following is a non-normative example of the minimal required
        SCIM representation in JSON format.</t>

        <artwork><![CDATA[
{
  "schemas": ["urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0"],
  "id": "005D0000001Az1u",
  "userName": "bjensen@example.com"
}

]]></artwork>
      </section>

      <section title="Full User Representation">
        <t>The following is a non-normative example of the fully populated
        SCIM representation in JSON format.</t>

        <artwork><![CDATA[

{
  "schemas": ["urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0"],
  "id": "005D0000001Az1u",
  "externalId": "701984",
  "userName": "bjensen@example.com",
  "name": {
    "formatted": "Ms. Barbara J Jensen III",
    "familyName": "Jensen",
    "givenName": "Barbara",
    "middleName": "Jane",
    "honorificPrefix": "Ms.",
    "honorificSuffix": "III"
  },
  "displayName": "Babs Jensen",
  "nickName": "Babs",
  "profileUrl": "https://login.example.com/bjensen",
  "emails": [
    {
      "value": "bjensen@example.com",
      "type": "work",
      "primary": true
    },
    {
      "value": "babs@jensen.org",
      "type": "home"
    }
  ],
  "addresses": [
    {
      "type": "work",
      "streetAddress": "100 Universal City Plaza",
      "locality": "Hollywood",
      "region": "CA",
      "postalCode": "91608",
      "country": "USA",
      "formatted": "100 Universal City Plaza\nHollywood, CA 91608 USA",
      "primary": true
    },
    {
      "type": "home",
      "streetAddress": "456 Hollywood Blvd",
      "locality": "Hollywood",
      "region": "CA",
      "postalCode": "91608",
      "country": "USA",
      "formatted": "456 Hollywood Blvd\nHollywood, CA 91608 USA"
    }
  ],
  "phoneNumbers": [
  {
    "value": "800-864-8377",
    "type": "work"
    },
    {
      "value": "818-123-4567",
      "type": "mobile"
    }
  ],
  "ims": [
    {
      "value": "someaimhandle",
      "type": "aim"
    }
  ],
  "photos": [
    {
      "value": "https://photos.example.com/profilephoto/72930000000Ccne/F",
      "type": "photo"
    },
    {
      "value": "https://photos.example.com/profilephoto/72930000000Ccne/T",
      "type": "thumbnail"
    }
  ],
  "userType": "Employee",
  "title": "Tour Guide",
  "preferredLanguage": "en_US",
  "locale": "en_US",
  "timezone": "America/Denver",
  "active":true,
  "groups": [
    {
      "display": "Tour Guides",
      "value": "00300000005N2Y6AA"
    },
    {
      "display": "Employees",
      "value": "00300000005N34H78"
    },
    {
      "display": "US Employees",
      "value": "00300000005N98YT1"
    }
  ],
  "meta": {
    "created": "2010-01-23T04:56:22Z",
    "lastModified": "2011-05-13T04:42:34Z"
  }
}
]]></artwork>
      </section>

      <section title="Enterprise User Extension Representation">
        <t>The following is a non-normative example of the fully populated
        User using the enterprise User extension in JSON format.</t>

        <artwork><![CDATA[

{
  "schemas": ["urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0", "urn:scim:schemas:extension:enterprise:1.0"],
  "id": "005D0000001Az1u",
  "externalId": "701984",
  "userName": "bjensen@example.com",
  "name": {
    "formatted": "Ms. Barbara J Jensen III",
    "familyName": "Jensen",
    "givenName": "Barbara",
    "middleName": "Jane",
    "honorificPrefix": "Ms.",
    "honorificSuffix": "III"
  },
  "displayName": "Babs Jensen",
  "nickName": "Babs",
  "profileUrl": "https://login.example.com/bjensen",
  "emails": [
    {
      "value": "bjensen@example.com",
      "type": "work",
      "primary": true
    },
    {
      "value": "babs@jensen.org",
      "type": "home"
    }
  ],
  "addresses": [
    {
      "streetAddress": "100 Universal City Plaza",
      "locality": "Hollywood",
      "region": "CA",
      "postalCode": "91608",
      "country": "USA",
      "formatted": "100 Universal City Plaza\nHollywood, CA 91608 USA",
      "type": "work",
      "primary": true
    },
    {
      "streetAddress": "456 Hollywood Blvd",
      "locality": "Hollywood",
      "region": "CA",
      "postalCode": "91608",
      "country": "USA",
      "formatted": "456 Hollywood Blvd\nHollywood, CA 91608 USA",
      "type": "home"
     }
  ],
  "phoneNumbers": [
    {
      "value": "800-864-8377",
      "type": "work"
    },
    {
      "value": "818-123-4567",
      "type": "mobile"
    }
  ],
  "ims": [
    {
      "value": "someaimhandle",
      "type": "aim"
    }
  ],
  "photos": [
    {
      "value": "https://photos.example.com/profilephoto/72930000000Ccne/F",
      "type": "photo"
    },
    {
      "value": "https://photos.example.com/profilephoto/72930000000Ccne/T",
      "type": "thumbnail"
    }
  ],
  "userType": "Employee",
  "title": "Tour Guide",
  "preferredLanguage": "en_US",
  "locale": "en_US",
  "timezone": "America/Denver",
  "active":true,
  "groups": [
    {
      "value": "00300000005N2Y6AA",
      "display": "Tour Guides"
    },
    {
      "value": "00300000005N34H78",
      "display": "Employees"
    },
    {
      "value": "00300000005N98YT1",
      "display": "US Employees"
    }
  ],
  "urn:scim:schemas:extension:enterprise:1.0": {
    "employeeNumber": "701984",
    "costCenter": "4130",
    "organization": "Universal Studios",
    "division": "Theme Park",
    "department": "Tour Operations",
    "manager": {
      "managerId": "005D0000001AQRE",
      "displayName": "John Smith"
    }
  },
  "meta": {
    "created": "2010-01-23T04:56:22Z",
    "lastModified": "2011-05-13T04:42:34Z"
  }
}

	]]></artwork>
      </section>

      <section title="Group Representation">
        <t>The following is a non-normative example of SCIM Group
        representation in JSON format.</t>

        <artwork><![CDATA[

{
  "schemas": ["urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0"],
  "id": "00300000005N98YT1",
  "displayName": "Tour Guides",
  "members": [
    {
      "value": "005D0000001Az1u",
      "display": "Babs Jensen"
    },
    {
      "value": "005D0000001AQRE",
      "display": "Mandy Pepperidge"
    }
  ]
}

]]></artwork>
      </section>


<section title="Service Provider Configuration Representation">
        <t>The following is a non-normative example of the SCIM Service Provider Configuration
        representation in JSON format.</t>

        <artwork><![CDATA[
{
  "schemas": ["urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0"],
  "documentationUrl":"http://example.com/help/scim.html",
  "patch": {
    "supported":true
  },
  "bulk": {
    "supported":true,
    "maxOperations":1000,
    "maxPayloadSize":1024
  },
  "filter": {
    "supported":true,
    "maxResults": 200
  },
  "changePassword" : {
    "supported":true
  },
  "sort": {
    "supported":true
  },
  "etag": {
    "supported":true
  },
  "authenticationSchemes": [
    {
      "name": "OAuth Bearer Token",
      "description": "Authentication Scheme using the OAuth Bearer Token Standard",
      "specUrl":"http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-oauth-v2-bearer-01",
      "documentationUrl":"http://example.com/help/oauth.html",
      "type":"OAuthBearerToken",
      "primary": true
    },
    {
      "name": "HTTP Basic",
      "description": "Authentication Scheme using the Http Basic Standard",
      "specUrl":"http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2617.txt",
      "documentationUrl":"http://example.com/help/httpBasic.html",
      "type":"HttpBasic"
     }
  ]
}

]]></artwork>
      </section>
  <section title="Resource Schema Representation">
        <t>The following is a normative example of the SCIM Resource Schema
        representation in JSON format.</t>

        <artwork><![CDATA[
{
  "id":"urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0:User",
  "name":"User",
  "description":"Core User",
  "schema":"urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0",
  "queryEndpoint":"/Users",
  "attributes":[
    {
      "name":"id",
      "type":"string",
      "plural":false,
      "description":"Unique identifier for the SCIM resource as defined by the Service Provider. Each representation of the resource MUST include a non-empty id value. This identifier MUST be unique across the Service Provider's entire set of resources. It MUST be a stable, non-reassignable identifier that does not change when the same resource is returned in subsequent requests. The value of the id attribute is always issued by the Service Provider and MUST never be specified by the Service Consumer. REQUIRED.",
      "schema":"urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0",
      "readOnly":true,
      "required":true,
      "caseExact":false
    },
    {
      "name":"name",
      "type":"complex",
      "plural":false,
      "description":"The components of the user's real name. Providers MAY return just the full name as a single string in the formatted sub-attribute, or they MAY return just the individual component attributes using the other sub-attributes, or they MAY return both. If both variants are returned, they SHOULD be describing the same name, with the formatted name indicating how the component attributes should be combined. OPTIONAL.",
      "schema":"urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0",
      "readOnly":false,
      "required":false,
      "caseExact":false,
      "subAttributes":[
        {
          "name":"formatted",
          "type":"string",
          "plural":false,
          "description":"The full name, including all middle names, titles, and suffixes as appropriate, formatted for display (e.g. Ms. Barbara J Jensen, III.). OPTIONAL." ,
          "readOnly":false,
          "required":false,
          "caseExact":false
        },
        {
          "name":"familyName",
          "type":"string",
          "plural":false,
          "description":"The family name of the User, or Last Name in most Western languages (e.g. Jensen given the full name Ms. Barbara J Jensen, III.). OPTIONAL",
          "readOnly":false,
          "required":false,
          "caseExact":false
        },
        {
          "name":"givenName",
          "type":"string",
          "plural":false,
          "description":"The given name of the User, or First Name in most Western languages (e.g. Barbara given the full name Ms. Barbara J Jensen, III.). OPTIONAL.",
          "readOnly":false,
          "required":false,
          "caseExact":false
        },
        {
          "name":"middleName",
          "type":"string",
          "plural":false,
          "description":"The middle name(s) of the User (e.g. Robert given the full name Ms. Barbara J Jensen, III.). OPTIONAL.",
          "readOnly":false,
          "required":false,
          "caseExact":false
        },
        {
          "name":"honorificPrefix",
          "type":"string",
          "plural":false,
          "description":"The honorific prefix(es) of the User, or Title in most Western languages (e.g. Ms. given the full name Ms. Barbara J Jensen, III.). OPTIONAL.",
          "readOnly":false,
          "required":false,
          "caseExact":false
        },
        {
          "name":"honorificSuffix",
          "type":"string",
          "plural":false,
          "description":"The honorific suffix(es) of the User, or Suffix in most Western languages (e.g. III. given the full name Ms. Barbara J Jensen, III.). OPTIONAL.",
          "readOnly":false,
          "required":false,
          "caseExact":false
        }
      ]
     },
     {
       "name":"emails",
       "type":"string",
       "plural":true,
       "description":"E-mail addresses for the user. The value SHOULD be canonicalized by the Service Provider, e.g. bjensen@example.com instead of bjensen@EXAMPLE.COM. Canonical Type values of work, home, and other. OPTIONAL.",
       "schema":"urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0",
       "readOnly":false,
       "required":false,
       "caseExact":false,
       "pluralTypes":["work","home","other"]
     },
     {
       "name":"addresses",
       "type":"complex",
       "plural":true,
       "description":"A physical mailing address for this User, as described in (address Element). Canonical Type Values of work, home, and other. The value attribute is a complex type with the following sub-attributes. OPTIONAL.",
       "schema":"urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0",
       "readOnly":false,
       "required":false,
       "caseExact":false,
       "pluralTypes":["work","home","other"],
       "subAttributes":[
         {
           "name":"formatted",
           "type":"string",
           "plural":false,
           "description":"The full mailing address, formatted for display or use with a mailing label. This attribute MAY contain newlines. OPTIONAL.",
           "readOnly":false,
           "required":false,
           "caseExact":false
         },
         {
           "name":"streetAddress",
           "type":"string",
           "plural":false,
           "description":"The full street address component, which may include house number, street name, PO BOX, and multi-line extended street address information. This attribute MAY contain newlines. OPTIONAL.",
           "readOnly":false,
           "required":false,
           "caseExact":false
         },
         {
           "name":"locality",
           "type":"string",
           "plural":false,
           "description":"The city or locality component. OPTIONAL.",
           "readOnly":false,
           "required":false,
           "caseExact":false
         },
         {
           "name":"region",
           "type":"string",
           "plural":false,
           "description":"The state or region component. OPTIONAL.",
           "readOnly":false,
           "required":false,
           "caseExact":false
         },
         {
           "name":"postalCode",
           "type":"string",
           "plural":false,
           "description":"The zipcode or postal code component. OPTIONAL.",
           "readOnly":false,
           "required":false,
           "caseExact":false
         },
         {
           "name":"country",
           "type":"string",
           "plural":false,
           "description":"The country name component. OPTIONAL.",
           "readOnly":false,
           "required":false,
           "caseExact":false
         }
       ]
     },
     {
       "name":"employeeNumber",
       "type":"string",
       "plural":false,
       "description":"Numeric or alphanumeric identifier assigned to a person, typically based on order of hire or association with an organization. Single valued. OPTIONAL.",
       "schema":"urn:scim:schemas:extension:enterprise:1.0",
       "readOnly":false,
       "required":false,
       "caseExact":false
     }
   ]
}

]]></artwork>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="xml_representation" title="XML Representation">
      <section title="Minimal Representation">
        <t>The following is a non-normative example of the minimal required
        SCIM User representation in XML format.</t>

        <artwork><![CDATA[

<SCIM xmlns="urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0">
  <id>005D0000001Az1u</id>
  <userName>bjensen@example.com</userName>
</SCIM>

]]></artwork>
      </section>

      <section title="Full Representation">
        <t>The following is a non-normative example of the fully populated
        SCIM representation in XML format.</t>

        <artwork><![CDATA[

<SCIM xmlns="urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0">
  <id>005D0000001Az1u</id>
  <externalId>701984</externalId>
  <userName>bjensen@example.com</userName>
  <name>
    <formatted>Ms. Babs J Jensen III</formatted>
    <familyName>Jensen</familyName>
    <givenName>Barbara</givenName>
    <middleName>Jane</middleName>
    <honorificPrefix>Ms.</honorificPrefix>
    <honorificSuffix>III</honorificSuffix>
  </name>
  <displayName>Babs Jensen</displayName>
  <nickName>Babs</nickName>
  <profileUrl>https://login.example.com/bjensen</profileUrl>
  <emails>
    <email>
      <value>bjensen@example.com</value>
      <type>work</type>
      <primary>true</primary>
    </email>
    <email>
      <value>babs@jensen.com</value>
      <type>home</type>
    </email>
  </emails>
  <addresses>
    <address>
      <formatted>100 Universal City Plaza\nHollywood, CA 91608 USA</formatted>
      <streetAddress>100 Universal City Plaza</streetAddress>
      <locality>Hollywood</locality>
      <region>CA</region>
      <postalCode>91608</postalCode>
      <country>USA</country>
      <type>work</type>
      <primary>true</primary>
    </address>
	<address>
      <formatted>456 Hollywood Blvd\nHollywood, CA 91608 USA</formatted>
      <streetAddress>456 Hollywood Blvd</streetAddress>
      <locality>San Francisco</locality>
      <region>CA</region>
      <postalCode>91608</postalCode>
      <country>USA</country>
      <type>home</type>
    </address>
  </addresses>
  <phoneNumbers>
    <phoneNumber>
      <value>800-864-8377</value>
      <type>work</type>
    </phoneNumber>
    <phoneNumber>
      <value>818-123-4567</value>
      <type>mobile</type>
    </phoneNumber>
  </phoneNumbers>
  <ims>
    <im>
      <value>someaimhandle</value>
      <type>aim</type>
    </im>
  </ims>
  <photos>
  <photo>
    <value>https://photos.example.com/profilephoto/72930000000Ccne/F</value>
    <type>photo</type>
   </photo>
   <photo>
    <value>https://photos.example.com/profilephoto/72930000000Ccne/T</value>
    <type>thumbnail</type>
   </photo>
  </photos>
  <userType>Employee</userType>
  <title>Tour Guide</title>
  <preferredLanguage>en_US</preferredLanguage>
  <locale>en_US</locale>
  <timezone>America/Denver</timezone>
  <active>true</active>
  <groups>
    <group>
      <value>00300000005N2Y6AA</value>
      <display>Tour Guides</display>
    </group>
    <group>
      <value>00300000005N34H78</value>
      <display>Employees</display>
    </group>
    <group>
      <value>00300000005N98YT1</value>
      <display>US Employees</display>
    </group>
  </groups>
  <meta>
    <created>2010-01-23T04:56:22Z</created>
    <lastModified>2011-05-13T04:42:34Z</lastModified>
  </meta>
</SCIM>

]]></artwork>
      </section>

      <section title="Enterprise User Extension Representation">
        <t>The following is a non-normative example of the fully populated
        User using the enterprise User extension in XML format.</t>

        <artwork><![CDATA[

<SCIM xmlns="urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0" xmlns:enterprise="urn:scim:schemas:extension:enterprise:1.0">
  <id>005D0000001Az1u</id>
  <externalId>701984</externalId>
  <userName>bjensen@example.com</userName>
  <name>
    <formatted>Ms. Babs J Jensen III</formatted>
    <familyName>Jensen</familyName>
    <givenName>Barbara</givenName>
    <middleName>Jane</middleName>
    <honorificPrefix>Ms.</honorificPrefix>
    <honorificSuffix>III</honorificSuffix>
  </name>
  <displayName>Babs Jensen</displayName>
  <nickName>Babs</nickName>
  <profileUrl>https://login.example.com/bjensen</profileUrl>
  <title>Tour Guide</title>
  <userType>Employee</userType>
  <preferredLanguage>en_US</preferredLanguage>
  <locale>en_US</locale>
  <timezone>America/Denver</timezone>
  <active>true</active>
  <emails>
    <email>
      <value>bjensen@example.com</value>
      <type>work</type>
      <primary>true</primary>
    </email>
    <email>
      <value>babs@jensen.com/value>
      <type>home</type>
    </email>
  </emails>
  <addresses>
    <address>
	  <formatted>100 Universal City Plaza\nHollywood, CA 91608 USA</formatted>
	  <streetAddress>100 Universal City Plaza</streetAddress>
	  <locality>Hollywood</locality>
	  <region>CA</region>
	  <postalCode>91608</postalCode>
      <country>USA</country>
	 <type>work</type>
	 <primary>true</primary>
    </address>
	<address>
	  <formatted>456 Hollywood Blvd\nHollywood, CA 91608 USA</formatted>
	  <streetAddress>456 Hollywood Blvd</streetAddress>
	  <locality>San Francisco</locality>
      <region>CA</region>
      <postalCode>91608</postalCode>
      <country>USA</country>
	 <type="home">
	</address>
  </addresses>
  <phoneNumbers>
    <phoneNumber>
      <value>800-864-8377</value>
      <type>work</type>
    </phoneNumber>
    <phoneNumber>
      <value>818-123-4567</value>
      <type>mobile</type>
    </phoneNumber>
  </phoneNumbers>
  <ims>
    <im>
     <value>someaimhandle</value>
     <type>aim</type>
     </im>
  </ims>
  <photos>
    <photo>
     <value>https://photos.example.com/profilephoto/72930000000Ccne/F</value>
     <type>photo></type>
    </photo>
    <photo>
     <value>https://photos.example.com/profilephoto/72930000000Ccne/T</value>
     <type>thumbnail></type>
    </photo>
  </photos>
  <groups>
    <group>
      <display>Tour Guides</display>
      <value>00300000005N2Y6AA</value>
    </group>
    <group>
      <display>Employees</display>
      <value>00300000005N34H78</value>
    </group>
    <group>
      <display>US Employees</display>
      <value>00300000005N98YT1</value>
    </group>
  </groups>
  <enterprise:employeeNumber>701984</enterprise:employeeNumber>
  <enterprise:manager managerId="005D0000001AQRE">Mandy Pepperidge</enterprise:manager>
  <enterprise:costCenter>4130</enterprise:costCenter>
  <enterprise:organization>Universal Studios</enterprise:organization>
  <enterprise:division>Theme Park</enterprise:division>
  <enterprise:department>Tour Operations</enterprise:department>
  <meta>
    <created>2010-01-23T04:56:22Z</created>
    <lastModified>2011-05-13T04:42:34Z</lastModified>
  </meta>
</SCIM>

	]]></artwork>
      </section>

      <section title="Group Representation">
        <t>The following is a non-normative example of a SCIM Group
        representation in XML format.</t>

        <artwork><![CDATA[

<SCIM xmlns="urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0">
  <id>00300000005N98YT1</id>
  <displayName>Tour Guides</displayName>
  <members>
    <member>
     <value>005D0000001Az1u</value>
     <display>Babs Jensen</display>
    </member>
    <member>
	  <value>005D0000001AQRE</value>
	  <display>Mandy Pepperidge</display>
    </member>
  </members>
</SCIM>

]]></artwork>
      </section>
    </section>
    <appendix title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The SCIM Community would like to thank the following people for the
      work they've done in the research, formulation, drafting, editing, and
      support of this specification.</t>

      <t>
        <list style="empty">
          <t>Chuck Mortimore (cmortimore@salesforce.com) &lt;editor&gt;</t>

          <t>Patrick Harding (pharding@pingidentity.com) &lt;author&gt;</t>

          <t>Paul Madsen (pmadsen@pingidentity.com) &lt;author&gt;</t>

          <t>Joseph Smarr (jsmarr@google.com) &lt;author&gt;</t>

          <t>Sidharth Choudhury (schoudhury@salesforce.com)</t>

          <t>...</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>Special thanks to Joeseph Smarr, who's excellent work on the Portable
      Contacts Specification <xref target="PortableContacts" /> provided the
      basis for much of the SCIM schema structure and text.</t>
    </appendix>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <reference anchor="PortableContacts">
        <front>
          <title>Portable Contacts 1.0 Draft C - Schema Only</title>

          <author fullname="Joeseph Smarr" initials="J." surname="Smarr">
            <organization abbrev="plaxo">Plaxo</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="5" month="August" year="2008" />
        </front>

        <format target="http://www.portablecontacts.net/draft-schema.html"
                type="HTML" />
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
