<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-scim-core-schema-01" ipr="trust200902">
  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>

  <?rfc tocdepth="2" ?>

  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>

  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

  <?rfc strict="no" ?>

  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>

  <?rfc private="Draft" ?>

  <front>
    <title abbrev="scim-core-schema-01">Simple Cloud Identity Management: Core
    Schema 1.0 - draft 1</title>

    <author fullname="Chuck Mortimore" initials="C." role="editor"
            surname="Mortimore">
      <organization abbrev="Salesforce">Salesforce.com</organization>

      <address>
        <email>cmortimore@salesforce.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Patrick Harding" initials="P." surname="Harding">
      <organization abbrev="Ping">Ping Identity</organization>

      <address>
        <email>pharding@pingidentity.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Paul Madsen" initials="P." surname="Madsen">
      <organization abbrev="Ping">Ping Identity</organization>

      <address>
        <email>pmadsen@pingidentity.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Joseph Smarr" initials="J." surname="Smarr">
      <organization abbrev="Google">Google</organization>

      <address>
        <email>jsmarr@google.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="30" month="April" year="2011" />

    <abstract>
      <t>The Simple Cloud Identity Management (SCIM) specification is designed
      to make managing user identity in cloud based applications and services
      easier. The specification suite seeks to build upon experience with
      existing schemas and deployments, placing specific emphasis on
      simplicity of development and integration, while applying existing
      authentication, authorization, and privacy models. It's intent is to
      reduce the cost and complexity of user management operations by
      providing a common user schema and extension model, as well as binding
      documents to provide patterns for exchanging this schema using standard
      protocols. In essence, make it fast, cheap, and easy to move users in
      to, out of, and around the cloud.</t>

      <t>This document provides a platform neutral schema and extension model
      for representing users for exchange and use with cloud service providers
      as well as standard serializations of that schema using JSON and
      XML.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="rnc" title="Requirements Notation and Conventions">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119" />
      .</t>

      <t>Throughout this document, values are quoted to indicate that they are
      to be taken literally. When using these values in protocol messages, the
      quotes MUST NOT be used as part of the value.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">
      <t>The following terms are defined by this specification:</t>

      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="foo">bar</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="overview" title="Overview">
      <t>While there are existing standards for describing and exchanging user
      information, many of these standards can be difficult to implement
      and/or use wire protocols that do not easily traverse firewalls nor
      easily layer onto existing web protocols. As a result, many cloud
      providers provide their own non-standard APIs for managing users within
      their services. This increases both the cost and complexity associated
      with organizations adopting products and services from multiple cloud
      providers as they must perform redundant integration development.
      Similarly, cloud services providers seeking to interoperate with
      multiple application marketplaces or cloud identity providers must be
      redundantly integrated.</t>

      <t>SCIM seeks to simplify this problem through a simple to implement
      specification suite that provides a common user schema and extension
      model, as well as binding documents to provide patterns for exchanging
      this schema using standard protocols. It draws inspiration and best
      practice, building upon existing user APIs and schemas from a wide
      variety of sources including, but not limited to, existing APIs exposed
      by cloud providers, PortableContacts, and LDAP directory services.</t>

      <t>This document provides a platform neutral schema and extension model
      for representing users for exchange and use with cloud service providers
      as well as standard serializations of that schema using JSON and XML.
      Additional binding documents provide a standard REST API, as well as use
      of SCIM schema over federation protocols such as SAML and OpenID</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="schema_structure" title="SCIM Schema Structure">
      <t>SCIM schema provides a minimal core schema for representing users,
      encompassing common attributes found in many existing deployments and
      schemas.</t>

      <t>Each field is defined as either a Singular Field, in which case there
      MUST NOT be more than one instance of that field per user, or as a
      Plural Field, in which case any number of instances of that field MAY be
      present per user. The only exception to this is a "schema" field used in
      representations that lack native support for expressing schemas such as
      JSON. This field allows introspection of the supported schema version
      for a SCIM representation as well any schema extensions supported by
      that representation. The 'schema' field is an array of strings, and
      values must by URIs designated by the corresponding schema
      definition.</t>

      <t>SCIM information is formatted using labeled attributes with either
      structured or unstructured string data. Each attribute label uses
      camelCase notation. Each attribute value consists of one of the
      following types:</t>

      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Simple">A single string attribute which MAY specify a
          REQUIRED data format or allow any string. A simple field MAY contain
          Canonical Values specified, in which case Service Providers SHOULD
          try to conform to those values if appropriate, but MAY provide
          alternate string values to represent additional values.</t>

          <t hangText="Boolean">A special case of a Simple Field with two
          legal values: true and false. Values are case-sensitive..</t>

          <t hangText="Complex">A multi-value attribute containing any
          combination of other attributes. Complex attributes are defined by
          listing the child attributes and their types. For most Complex
          Fields, the value sub-field contains the Major Value of that field
          (i.e. the primary piece of information described by that field), and
          the other fields provide additional meta-data.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>Unless otherwise specified, all fields are optional and of type
      xs:string. Also, unless specified, all field values MUST NOT contain any
      newline characters (\r or \n).</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="schema" title="SCIM Schema">
      <section title="schemas Field">
        <t>SCIM schema is identified using the following URI:
        'urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0' ( Note: we're currently using an
        un-registered urn while in draft form)</t>

        <t>Where a specific representation has existing support for expressing
        schema, the traditional convention of that representation MUST be
        applied. For example, when representing users using XML, XML Namespace
        should be used.</t>

        <t>When a representation does not explicitly provide support for
        indicating a schema, such as JSON, a 'schemas' field is used to
        indicate the version of CloudSchema as well as any schema
        extensions.</t>

        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="schemas">The schemas field is an array of string
            which allows introspection of the supported schema version for a
            SCIM representation as well any schema extensions supported by
            that representation. Each string value must be a unique URI. This
            specification defines the following uri
            'urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0' All representations of SCIM schema
            MUST include a non-zero value array with a value of
            'urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0' Duplicate values MUST NOT be included.
            Ordering on the array is ignored has no impact on behavior.
            REQUIRED where applicable.</t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <section title="Schema Extension Model">
          <t>SCIM schema follows an object extension model similar to
          ObjectClasses used in LDAP. Unlike LDAP there is no inheritance
          model; all extensions additive. ( similar to auxiliary objectClasses
          ) Each value indicates additive schema that may exist in a SCIM
          representation as specified by extensions not defined in this suite.
          Each schema extension must identify a canonical URI used to identify
          the extension. Schema Extensions MUST follow the rules of singular
          and plural field structured defined in this core schema
          specification. Schema extensions MUST NOT override or redefine any
          schema defined in this core specification. For representations that
          support expressing schema, the native convention MUST be used (For
          instance, XML Namespace). When the the 'schema' field is being used,
          additional URIs MUST be specified in the 'schema' field array.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Identifiers">
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="id">Unique identifier for the User as defined by the
            Service Provider. Each representation of the User MUST include a
            non-empty id value. This identifier MUST be unique across the
            Service Provider's entire set of Users. It MUST be a stable,
            non-reassignable identifier that does not change when the same
            user is returned in subsequent requests. The value of the id
            attribute is always issued be the Service Provider and can never
            be specified by the Service Consumer. REQUIRED.</t>

            <t hangText="externalId">Unique identifier for the User as defined
            by the Service Consumer. The externalId may simplify
            identification of the User between Service Consumer and Service
            provider by allowing the consumer to refer to the User with it's
            own identifier, obviating the need to store a local mapping
            between the local identifier of the user and the identifier used
            by the Service Provider. Each User MAY include a non-empty
            externalId value. The value of the externalId attribute is always
            issued be the Service Consumer and can never be specified by the
            Service Provider. This identifier MUST be unique across the
            Service Consumer's entire set of Users. It MUST be a stable,
            non-reassignable identifier that does not change when the same
            user is returned in subsequent requests. The Service Provider MUST
            always interpret the externalId as scoped to the Service
            Consumer's tenant. OPTIONAL.</t>

            <t hangText="userName">Unique identifier for the User, typically
            used by the user to directly authenticate to the service provider.
            Often displayed to the user as their unique identifier within the
            system ( as opposed to id or externalId, which are generally
            opaque and not user-friendly identifiers ) Each User MUST include
            a non-empty userName value. This identifier MUST be unique across
            the Service Consumer's entire set of Users. It MUST be a stable ID
            that does not change when the same user is returned in subsequent
            requests. REQUIRED.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Singular Fields">
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="name">The broken-out components and fully formatted
            version of the user's real name, as described in Section N (name
            Element). OPTIONAL.</t>

            <t hangText="displayName">The name of the User, suitable for
            display to end-users. Each User returned MAY include a non-empty
            displayName value. The name SHOULD be the full name of the User
            being described if known (e.g. Babs Jensen or Ms. Barbara J
            Jensen, III), but MAY be a username or handle, if that is all that
            is available (e.g. bjensen). The value provided SHOULD be the
            primary textual label by which this User is normally displayed by
            the Service Provider when presenting it to end-users. OPTIONAL</t>

            <t hangText="nickName">The casual way to address the user in real
            life, e.g. "Bob" or "Bobby" instead of "Robert". This field SHOULD
            NOT be used to represent a user's username (e.g. bjensen or
            mpepperidge). OPTIONAL.</t>

            <t hangText="profileUrl">URL to a page representing the user's
            online profile. OPTIONAL.</t>

            <t hangText="employeeNumber">Numeric or alphanumeric identifier
            assigned to a person, typically based on order of hire or
            association with an organization. Single valued. OPTIONAL.</t>

            <t hangText="userType">Used to identify the organization to user
            relationship. Typical values used will be "Contractor",
            "Employee", "Intern", "Temp", "External", and "Unknown" but any
            value may be used. OPTIONAL.</t>

            <t hangText="title">The user&rsquo;s business title, such as
            &ldquo;Vice President.&rdquo; OPTIONAL.</t>

            <t hangText="manager">The user's manager. TODO - does this need to
            be a complex type that allows us to actually represent and
            traverse hierarchy? OPTIONAL.</t>

            <t hangText="preferredLanguage">Used to indicate an individual's
            preferred written or spoken language. Generally used for
            localizing the interface presented to the user. OPTIONAL. TODO -
            what ISO code list should we use here?</t>

            <t hangText="locale">Used to indicate the user's default location
            for purposes of localizing items such as currency, date time
            format, numerical representations, etc. OPTIONAL. TODO - what ISO
            code list should we use here?</t>

            <t hangText="utcOffset">The offset from UTC of the Users's default
            time zone. The value MUST conform to the offset portion of
            xs:dateTime, e.g. -08:00. OPTIONAL.</t>

            <t hangText="costCenter">Identifies the name of a cost center.
            OPTIONAL.</t>

            <t hangText="organization">Identifies the name of an organization.
            OPTIONAL.</t>

            <t hangText="division">Identifies the name of a division.
            OPTIONAL.</t>

            <t hangText="department">Identifies the name of a department.
            OPTIONAL.</t>

            <t hangText="meta">The broken-out components and fully formatted
            version of meta data about this User account, as described in
            Section N (meta Element). OPTIONAL.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Plural Fields">
        <t>Unless specified otherwise, all Plural Fields have the same three
        standard sub-fields:</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="value">The primary value of this field, e.g. the
            actual e-mail address, phone number, or URL. Each non-empty Plural
            Field value MUST contain at least the value sub-field, but all
            other sub-fields are optional.</t>

            <t hangText="type">The type of field for this instance, usually
            used to label the preferred function of the given user
            information. Unless otherwise specified, this string value
            specifies Canonical Values of work, home, and other.</t>

            <t hangText="primary">A Boolean value indicating whether this
            instance of the Plural Field is the primary or preferred value of
            for this field, e.g. the preferred mailing address or primary
            e-mail address. Service Providers MUST NOT mark more than one
            instance of the same Plural Field as primary="true", and MAY
            choose not to mark any fields as primary, if this information is
            not available. For efficiency, Service Providers SHOULD NOT mark
            all non-primary fields with primary="false", but should instead
            omit this sub-field for all non-primary instances.</t>
          </list>When returning Plural Fields, Service Providers SHOULD
        canonicalize the value returned, if appropriate (e.g. for e-mail
        addresses and URLs). Providers MAY return the same value more than
        once with different types (e.g. the same e-mail address may used for
        work and home), but SHOULD NOT return the same (type, value)
        combination more than once per Plural Field, as this complicates
        processing by the Consumer.</t>

        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="emails">E-mail addresses for the user. The value
            SHOULD be canonicalized by the Service Provider, e.g.
            bjensen@example.com instead of bjensen@EXAMPLE.COM. OPTIONAL.</t>

            <t hangText="phoneNumbers">Phone numbers for the user. No
            canonical value is assumed here. In addition to the standard
            Canonical Values for type, this field also defines the additional
            Canonical Values mobile, fax, and pager. OPTIONAL.</t>

            <t hangText="ims">Instant messaging address for the user. No
            official canonicalization rules exist for all instant messaging
            addresses, but Service Providers SHOULD remove all whitespace and
            convert the address to lowercase, if this is appropriate for the
            service this IM address is used for. Instead of the standard
            Canonical Values for type, this field defines the following
            Canonical Values to represent currently popular IM services: aim,
            gtalk, icq, xmpp, msn, skype, qq, and yahoo. OPTIONAL.</t>

            <t hangText="photos">URL of a photo of the user. The value SHOULD
            be a canonicalized URL, and MUST point to an actual image file
            (e.g. a GIF, JPEG, or PNG image file) rather than to a web page
            containing an image. Service Providers MAY return the same image
            at different sizes, though it is recognized that no standard for
            describing images of various sizes currently exists. Note that
            this field SHOULD NOT be used to send down arbitrary photos taken
            by this user, but specifically profile photos of the user suitable
            for display when describing the user. Instead of the standard
            Canonical Values for type, this field defines the following
            Canonical Values to represent popular photo sizes: photo,
            thumbnail. OPTIONAL.</t>

            <t hangText="addresses">A physical mailing address for this User,
            as described in (address Element). OPTIONAL.</t>

            <t hangText="groups">A list of groups or roles that the user
            belongs to. The values are meant to enable expression of common
            group or role based access control models, although no explicit
            authorization model is defined. It is intended that the semantics
            of group membership and any behavior or authorization granted as a
            result of membership are defined by the Service Provider and
            considered out of scope for this specification. This value has NO
            canonical types and removes the standard canonical types.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="name Element">
        <t>The components of the user's real name. Providers MAY return just
        the full name as a single string in the formatted sub-field, or they
        MAY return just the individual component fields using the other
        sub-fields, or they MAY return both. If both variants are returned,
        they SHOULD be describing the same name, with the formatted name
        indicating how the component fields should be combined.</t>

        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="formatted">The full name, including all middle names,
            titles, and suffixes as appropriate, formatted for display (e.g.
            Ms. Barbara J Jensen, III.). OPTIONAL.</t>

            <t hangText="familyName">The family name of the User, or "Last
            Name" in most Western languages (e.g. Jensen given the full name
            Ms. Barbara J Jensen, III.). OPTIONAL.</t>

            <t hangText="givenName">The given name of the User, or "First
            Name" in most Western languages (e.g. Barbara given the full name
            Ms. Barbara J Jensen, III.). OPTIONAL.</t>

            <t hangText="middleName">The middle name(s) of the User (e.g.
            Robert given the full name Ms. Barbara J Jensen, III.).
            OPTIONAL.</t>

            <t hangText="honorificPrefix">The honorific prefix(es) of the
            User, or "Title" in most Western languages (e.g. Ms. given the
            full name Ms. Barbara J Jensen, III.). OPTIONAL.</t>

            <t hangText="honorificSuffix">The honorifix suffix(es) of the
            User, or "Suffix" in most Western languages (e.g. III. given the
            full name Ms. Barbara J Jensen, III.). OPTIONAL.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="address Element">
        <t>The components of a physical mailing address. Service Providers MAY
        return just the full address as a single string in the formatted
        sub-field, or they MAY return just the individual component fields
        using the other sub-fields, or they MAY return both. If both variants
        are returned, they SHOULD be describing the same address, with the
        formatted address indicating how the component fields should be
        combined.</t>

        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="formatted">The full mailing address, formatted for
            display or use with a mailing label. This field MAY contain
            newlines. OPTIONAL</t>

            <t hangText="streetAddress">The full street address component,
            which may include house number, street name, PO BOX, and
            multi-line extended street address information. This field MAY
            contain newlines. OPTIONAL</t>

            <t hangText="locality">The city or locality component.
            OPTIONAL</t>

            <t hangText="region">The state or region component. OPTIONAL</t>

            <t hangText="postalCode">The zipcode or postal code component.
            OPTIONAL</t>

            <t hangText="country">The country name component. OPTIONAL. TODO
            what ISO code list should we use here?</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="meta Element">
        <t>Additional meta data related to the user's account, rather then the
        user themselves.</t>

        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="created">The date the User was first added to the
            Service Provider The value MUST be a valid xs:dateTime (e.g.
            2008-01-23T04:56:22Z). OPTIONAL.</t>

            <t hangText="lastModified">The most recent date the details of
            this User were updated at the Service Provider. The value MUST be
            a valid xd:dateTime (e.g. 2008-01-23T04:56:22Z). If this User has
            never been modified since its initial creation, the value MUST be
            the same as the value of created. OPTIONAL.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="json_representation" title="JSON Representation">
      <section title="Minimal Representation">
        <t>The following is a non-normative example of the minimal required
        SCIM representation in JSON</t>

        <artwork><![CDATA[

	{ 
	    "schemas": ["urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0"], 
	    "id": "005D0000001Az1u", 
	    "userName": "bjensen@example.com"
	}			

]]></artwork>
      </section>

      <section title="Full Representation">
        <t>The following is a non-normative example of the fully populated
        SCIM representation in JSON</t>

        <artwork><![CDATA[

	{ 
	    "schemas": ["urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0"], 
	    "id": "005D0000001Az1u", 
	    "externalId": "701984", 
	    "userName": "bjensen@example.com",
	    "name": {
	    	"formatted": "Ms. Barbara J Jensen III",
	        "familyName": "Jensen",
	        "givenName": "Barbara",
	        "middleName": "Jane",
	        "honorificPrefix": "Ms.",
	        "honorificSuffix": "III"
	    },
	    "displayName": "Babs Jensen",
	    "nickName": "Babs",
	    "profileUrl": "https://login.example.com/bjensen",
	    "emails": [
	        {
	          "value": "bjensen@example.com",
	          "type": "work",
	          "primary": true
	        },
	        {
	          "value": "babs@jensen.org",
	          "type": "home"
	        }
	    ],	
	    "addresses": [
	        {
	          "type": "work",
	          "streetAddress": "100 Universal City Plaza",
	          "locality": "Hollywood",
	          "region": "CA",
	          "postalCode": "91608",
	          "country": "USA",
	          "formatted": "100 Universal City Plaza\nHollywood, CA 91608 USA",
	          "primary": true
	        },
	        {
	          "type": "home",
	          "streetAddress": "456 Hollywood Blvd",
	          "locality": "Hollywood",
	          "region": "CA",
	          "postalCode": "91608",
	          "country": "USA",
	          "formatted": "456 Hollywood Blvd\nHollywood, CA 91608 USA"
	        }
	    ],
	    "phoneNumbers": [
	        {
	          "value": "800-864-8377",
	          "type": "work"
	        },
	        {
	          "value": "818-123-4567",
	          "type": "mobile"
	        }
	    ],
	    "ims": [
	        {
	          "value": "someaimhandle",
	          "type": "aim"
	        }
	    ],
	    "photos": [
	        {
	          "value": "https://photos.example.com/profilephoto/72930000000Ccne/F",
	          "type": "photo"
	        },
	        {
	          "value": "https://photos.example.com/profilephoto/72930000000Ccne/T",
	          "type": "thumbnail"
	        }
	    ],
	    "employeeNumber": "701984",
	    "userType": "Employee",
	    "title": "Tour Guide",
	    "manager": "Mandy Pepperidge",
	    "preferredLanguage": "en_US",
	    "locale": "en_US",
	    "utcOffset": "-08:00",
	    "costCenter": "4130",
	    "organization": "Universal Studios",
	    "division": "Theme Park",
	    "department": "Tour Operations",
	    "groups": [
	        {
	          "value": "Tour Guides",
	          "primary": true
	        },
	        {
	          "value": "Employees",
	        },
	        {
	          "value": "US Employees",
	        }
	    ],
	    "meta": {
	        "created": "2010-01-23T04:56:22Z",
	        "lastModified": "2011-05-13T04:42:34Z"
	    }
	}

]]></artwork>
      </section>

      <section title="Extended Representation">
        <t>The following is a non-normative example of SCIM representation
        that includes a fictional schema extension</t>

        <artwork><![CDATA[

	{ 
	    "schemas": ["urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0", "http://hrextension/"], 
	    "id": "005D0000001Az1u", 
	    "externalId": "701984", 
	    "userName": "bjensen@example.com",
	    "name": {
	        "familyName": "Jensen",
	        "givenName": "Barbara",
	    },
	    "gender": "female",
	    "birthday": "1942-04-26"
	}	

]]></artwork>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="xml_representation" title="XML Representation">
      <section title="Minimal Representation">
        <t>The following is a non-normative example of the minimal required
        SCIM representation in XML</t>

        <artwork><![CDATA[

	<SCIM xmlns="urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0">
	    <id>005D0000001Az1u</id>
	    <userName>bjensen@example.com</userName>
	</SCIM>
	
]]></artwork>
      </section>

      <section title="Full Representation">
        <t>The following is a non-normative example of the fully populated
        SCIM representation in XML</t>

        <artwork><![CDATA[

	<SCIM xmlns="urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0">
	    <id>005D0000001Az1u</id>
	    <externalId>701984</externalId>
	    <userName>bjensen@example.com</userName>
	    <name>
	    	<formatted>Ms. Babs J Jensen III</formatted>
	    	<familyName>Jensen</familyName>
	    	<givenName>Barbara</givenName>
	    	<middleName>Jane</middleName>
	    	<honorificPrefix>Ms.</honorificPrefix>
	    	<honorificSuffix>III</honorificSuffix>
	    </name>
	    <displayName>Babs Jensen</displayName>
	    <nickName>Babs</nickName>
	    <profileUrl>https://login.example.com/bjensen</profileUrl>
	    <emails>
	        <email type="work" primary="true">bjensen@example.com</email>
	        <email type="home">babs@jensen.com</email>
	    </emails>	
	    <addresses>
	        <address type="work" primary="true">
	            <formatted>100 Universal City Plaza\nHollywood, CA 91608 USA</formatted>
	            <streetAddress>100 Universal City Plaza</streetAddress>
	            <locality>Hollywood</locality>
	            <region>CA</region>
	            <postalCode>91608</postalCode>
	            <country>USA</country>
	        </address>
	        <address type="home">
	            <formatted>456 Hollywood Blvd\nHollywood, CA 91608 USA</formatted>
	            <streetAddress>456 Hollywood Blvd</streetAddress>
	            <locality>San Francisco</locality>
	            <region>CA</region>
	            <postalCode>91608</postalCode>
	            <country>USA</country>
	        </address>
	    </addresses>
	    <phoneNumbers>
	        <phoneNumber type="work">800-864-8377</phoneNumber>
	        <phoneNumber type="mobile">818-123-4567</phoneNumber>
	    </phoneNumbers>
	    <ims>
	        <im type="aim">someaimhandle</im>
	    </ims>
	    <photos>
	        <photo type="photo">https://photos.example.com/profilephoto/72930000000Ccne/F"</photo>
	        <photo type="thumbnail">https://photos.example.com/profilephoto/72930000000Ccne/T"</photo>
	    </photos>
	    <employeeNumber>701984</employeeNumber>
	    <userType>Employee</userType>
	    <title>Tour Guide</title>
	    <manager>Mandy Pepperidge</manager>
	    <gender>female</gender>
	    <preferredLanguage>en_US</preferredLanguage>
	    <locale>en_US</locale>
	    <utcOffset>-08:00</utcOffset>
	    <costCenter>4130</costCenter>
	    <organization>Universal Studios</organization>
	    <division>Theme Park</division>
	    <department>Tour Operations</department>
	    <groups>
	        <group primary="true">Tour Guides</group>
	        <group>Employees</group>
	        <group>US Employees</group>
	    </groups>    
	    <meta>
	        <created>2010-01-23T04:56:22Z</created>
	        <lastModified>2011-05-13T04:42:34Z</lastModified>
	    </meta>
	</SCIM>
	
]]></artwork>
      </section>

      <section title="Extended Representation">
        <t>The following is a non-normative example of SCIM XML representation
        that includes a fictional schema extension</t>

        <artwork><![CDATA[

	<SCIM xmlns="urn:scim:schemas:core:1.0" xmlns:hr="http://hrextension/">
	    <id>005D0000001Az1u</id>
	    <externalId>701984</externalId>
	    <userName>bjensen@example.com</userName>
	    <name>
	    	<familyName>Jensen</familyName>
	    	<givenName>Barbara</givenName>
	    </name>
	    <hr:gender>female</hr:gender>
	    <hr:birthday>1942-04-26</hr:birthday>
	</SCIM>

]]></artwork>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="TODO" title="TODO">
      <t>The following are outstanding work items</t>

      <t>Macro level issues<list style="symbols">
          <t>Refactor core schema so the core is tighter; create an enterprise
          focused extension, and allow for other extensions such as mobile and
          consumer </t>

          <t>Attempt to align schema with PoCo and OpenID Connect</t>

          <t>Add a top level groups object</t>

          <t>Debate the need for nested groups</t>

          <t>Debate the need for Service Provisioning</t>

          <t>Update plural attributes to deal with concerns around label and
          value</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Clerical Issues<list style="symbols">
          <t>Clarify language and use-cases around externalId</t>

          <t>Terms 'field' and 'attribute' seem frequent and interchangeable;
          use attribute</t>

          <t>Add a binarydata to the photo object. Make it only available for
          explicit read ( this is probably for the REST API ) </t>

          <t>Update language on singular vs plural emails </t>

          <t>Add a explicit DateTime value type</t>
        </list></t>

      <t />
    </section>

    <appendix title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The SCIM Community would like to thank the following people for the
      work they've done in the research, formulation, drafting, editing, and
      support of this specification.</t>

      <t>
        <list style="empty">
          <t>Chuck Mortimore (cmortimore@salesforce.com) &lt;editor&gt;</t>

          <t>Patrick Harding (pharding@pingidentity.com) &lt;author&gt;</t>

          <t>Paul Madsen (pmadsen@pingidentity.com) &lt;author&gt;</t>

          <t>Paul Madsen (pmadsen@pingidentity.com) &lt;author&gt;</t>

          <t>Joseph Smarr (jsmarr@google.com) &lt;author&gt;</t>

          <t>Sidharth Choudhury (schoudhury@salesforce.com)</t>

          <t>...</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>Special thanks to Joeseph Smarr, who's excellent work on the Portable
      Contacts Specification <xref target="PortableContacts" /> provided the
      basis for much of the SCIM schema structure and text.</t>
    </appendix>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <reference anchor="PortableContacts">
        <front>
          <title>Portable Contacts 1.0 Draft C - Schema Only</title>

          <author fullname="Joeseph Smarr" initials="J." surname="Smarr">
            <organization abbrev="plaxo">Plaxo</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="5" month="August" year="2008" />
        </front>

        <format target="http://www.portablecontacts.net/draft-schema.html"
                type="HTML" />
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
